<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The seconde parte of the booke called a Bucklar of the Catholyke fayeth conteyninge seuen chapiters / made by Rychard Smyth doctoure of diuinitie of Oxforde, &amp; reader of the same there.</title>
            <author>Smith, Richard, 1500-1563.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1555</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 145 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12487</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22817.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S989</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23150958</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23150958</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26296</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12487)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26296)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1781:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The seconde parte of the booke called a Bucklar of the Catholyke fayeth conteyninge seuen chapiters / made by Rychard Smyth doctoure of diuinitie of Oxforde, &amp; reader of the same there.</title>
                  <author>Smith, Richard, 1500-1563.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[175] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In ædibus Roberti Caly, typographi,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Excusum Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>mense Ianuarii anno. 1555.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum sol[u]m."</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [pi]⁴ A-K⁸ L⁴.</note>
                  <note>Preliminary pages repeated twice.</note>
                  <note>Includes marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained with print show-through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Peterborough Cathedral. Library.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Doctrines.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26296:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26296:1"/>
            <p>The ſeconde parte of the booke called a Bucklar of the Catholyke fayeth, conteyninge ſeuen cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piters: Made by Rychard Smyth doctoure of diuinitie of Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde, &amp; reader of the ſame there..</p>
            <p>¶ <hi>EXCVSVM LONDINI IN aedibus Roberti Caly, Typographi Menſe Ianuarii Anno. 1555. Cum priuilegio ad impris mendum ſol <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26296:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:26296:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:26296:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:26296:3"/>
            <head>¶ The contentes of this ſecond booke, whiche is d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ded into ſeuen chapiters.</head>
            <p>THat it is not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aweful for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to forſake his wyfe but onelye for aduoutrie, and that, if he forſake her for that cauſe, yet he may not marrye againe, as longe as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e lyueth, althoughe Peter Martyr, Iohan Hoper, &amp; ſuche other did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ach the coutrarie, againſte Goodes lawe and mans.</p>
            <p>ii. A co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futation of an abhominable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of Peter Martyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſetti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g furth, whiche William <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> yudal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> taught in his preface vpon the Epiſtle to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maines before his tranſlation, whiche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s that oure ſaluation conſiſteth onlye in God, and nothinge in vs, whiche wicked opinion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>keth cleane awaye mans free wyll from him.</p>
            <p>iii. The baptiſme of children, againſt all the Swing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ans, and not Peter Martyr onelye, and the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>abaptiſtes.</p>
            <p>iiii. That the ſoules of men departed
<pb facs="tcp:26296:4"/> doe not ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eape, but either they goe to heauen for thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> good workes, or e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to Hell for their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ell before dom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s daye.</p>
            <p>v. That it is lawefull and good to put fraunce, eſperaunce, or truſte in our good workes, nexte after God, as in his giftes, which thinge Luther, Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, Peter Martyr, &amp; ſemblable others <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Alſo that we maye lyue godlye for the heauenlye rewarde.</p>
            <p>vi. That Baptiſme is not onelye a ſigne &amp; a marke of our iuſtification &amp; profeſſion, nor onlye a ſeale and confir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mation of the ſame, as Peter Martyr and the authors of the catech<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſme, and articles ſetfurthe in kinge Edwarde the .vi. tyme falſlye a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d wickedlye do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſaye, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d teache.</p>
            <p>vii. That all godlye vowes, as the vowe of virginitie, of continual cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>titie, promiſed by a wydow, the vow of wylfull or voluntarie pouertie, and ſemblables ought<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by Gods lawe to be obſerued vnder payne of euerlaſty<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge damnation.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:26296:4"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:26296:5"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:26296:5"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:26296:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:26296:6"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>The ſeconde booke.</hi> The firſte chapiter.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>That it is not lawfull for a man to forſake his wife but onely for aduou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trie, and that, if he forſake her for that cauſe, yet he maye not marrye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, as longe as ſhee lyueth, althoughe Peter Martyr, Iohan Hoper, and ſuche other did t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ache the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trarie, againſt Gods lawe and mans.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſte playnely ſaieth. <hi>Ego dico uo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Math. v.</note> 
               <hi>etc</hi> But I ſay vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to you, who ſoeuer put<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth awaye hys wyfe (excepte it be for fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) cauſeth her to commit ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutrie, and who ſoeuer marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth her, that is deuorſed, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth matrimonie. Whiche thing Marke and Luke doe expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de <note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:26296:7"/> after ſuche ſorte, that we maye <note place="margin">Mar x. Luke. xvi.</note> perceiue euidently that Chriſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, that if anye man ſhoulde leaue hys wyfe for aduoutrie (for which cauſe only it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to forſake her) yet he ought not to marrye an other wyfe <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ora<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Gloſo interli. Haymo in, i. Cor. vii.</note> whiles ſhe liueth. For Marke ſayeth, who ſoeuer putteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye his wife, and marrieth an other, breaketh matrimonie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her, and if a woman for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake her huſbande, and marrye an other, ſhe committeth aduou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trie. <hi>S.</hi> Luke declareth the ſame ſaying thus. <hi>Ois qui dimittit u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rem ſua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> et aliam ducit, maechatur, &amp; qui d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſſam á uiro ducit, mae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chatur.</hi> Euery man, that forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his wyfe and marrieth an other, committeth aduoutrie, and he that marrieth her, which
<pb facs="tcp:26296:7"/> is for ſaken, committeth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>outrie.</p>
            <p>The holye and greate clerke S. Auſten did writte agaynſte Poilentius, becauſe he ſayed a man mighte lefullye marrye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, when he hadde forſaken his wyfe for aduoutrie, and he did alledge theſe two places of Marke, and Luke to proue his purpoſe, whiche writeth of that matter after this maner, expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding theſe wordes of S. Paule. I ſay not to them that are mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, <note place="margin">i Cor. vii. <hi>Tom i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i lib. lxxxiii <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ix, lxxxiii.</hi>
               </note> but our lorde co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth that the wyfe goe not from her huſbande, if ſhe doe, ſhe ſhoulde remain vnmarried, or els be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to her huſband. <hi>Vbi e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam</hi> 
               <note place="margin">oecumenus ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</note> 
               <hi>in telligitur, quòd ſi una<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lla cauſa, qua ſola relictio co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iugij per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittitur, mulier á uiro recell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:8"/> innupta perſeuerare debet, aut ſi ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinet, uiro potius reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciliari, uel correctouel tolera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>do, quàm al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri nubere. Sequitur aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; dicit.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Idem habet Tom. iiii. lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. de ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ca. xxv, &amp; xxvi.</note> 
               <hi>Et uir uxore<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> non dimittat, breui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>andem formam intimans in uiro, quam precipiebat in foemina, que ex precepto dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i inſinuauit. Hae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ille.</hi> In the which ſaying of S. Paule it is vnderſtand, that if the wyfe goe awaye from her huſbande for that onely cauſe, for the which alone the leauing of marriage is permitted, ſhee ought to continue vnmarried, or if ſhe liue not continently, ſhe oughte rather to be reconciled vnto her huſband, either amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, or e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to be tolerated, then to marrie vnto an other man. It followeth in S. Paule, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: And let not the man leaue
<pb facs="tcp:26296:8"/> hys wyfe. By whiche wordes S. Paule do the brieflye ſhewe, that the ſame fourme ought to be in the man whiche he did com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunde to be in the woman, that is to ſaye, that he leaue his wife onlye for aduoutrie, &amp; if he leaue her for that cauſe, he mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye not agayne.</p>
            <p>Saint Hierom alſo, is againſt Peter Martyr and Iohan Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, <note place="margin">Tom. ix. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mat. xix.</note> when he ſayeth thus. <hi>Quia poterat accidere, ut aliquis calumni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>am faceret innocenti, &amp; ob ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam nuptiarum copulam, veteri crimen impingeret, ſic iubetur pri orem dimittere uxorem, ut ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dam, uiuente prima, non habeat.</hi> For as muche as it myght haue chaunced, that ſome man ſhould <note place="margin">Note this againſt Iohn Hope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the white m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke</note> picke a quarell againſt his wife, or falſelye accuſe her of aduou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:9"/> and finde faulte with the firſte marriage, to be married agayne. He is ſo commaunded to forſake his firſte wyfe, that he maye not haue the ſeconde, whiles the firſte is alyue. The lyke he ſayeth of the woman, who is in thys point equal with her huſband, as S. Paule me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, <note place="margin">i. Cor, vii.</note> ſaying, that the huſbande hathe not power of his bodye, nor the wyfe of hers. He reproued a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man verye ſharplye becauſe ſhe <note place="margin">In epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aphio fa biole</note> forſoke her huſbande for aduou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trie, and was married to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man. Alſo he ſayeth expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding S. Paules wordes to the Corinthiens written of thys matt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er. <hi>Docet apoſtolus iux<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tom. ii. lib. i. contra Iouinia.</hi> i. Cor. vii.</note> 
               <hi>ſententiam domini, uxorem, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta cauſa fornicationis, non eſſe repudiandam, &amp; repduiatam uiuo
<pb facs="tcp:26296:9"/> marito, alteri non nubere, aut uiro ſuo reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciliari debere.</hi> Thapoſtle teacheth (ſaieth he) that the wife ought not to be put awaye, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the minde of our lord Chriſt, excepte for her aduoutrie, and that ſhe being ſo forſaken of her huſbande for that, ought not to marrye an other, while her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande liueth, or els ſhe ought to be reconciled vnto her huſband.</p>
            <p>Alſo he ſayeth, I founde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briefe <note place="margin">Tom. iii. epiſt. ad Amandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> letter ioyned vnto thine Epiſtle, and thy commentarie, in whiche theſe wordes were written. Aſke or demaunde of him, that is to ſaye of me, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a woman, which, her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande being forſaken for aduou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trie, &amp; another married thorow force, maye without penaunce be receaued in to the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:26296:10"/> of the churche that man yet alyue, whiche ſhe had forſaken for his aduoutrie. The whiche thing when I readde, I remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bred thys verſe of Dauid. <note place="margin">Pſalm. 140.</note>
            </p>
            <p>They doe it to finde excuſes for the defenſe of their ſynnes. We al are men that fauour our owne vices, and doe impute vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the neceſſitie of nature, that thinge, whiche we doe commit through our own frewyl. As if <note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s free wyll.</note> a you<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e: I ſuffer force, or violence of my bodye, the heate of my fleaſhe driueth or inforceth me to ſynne. The inſtrumentes of my priuie mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bres, and the complexion of my bodie deſier a womans com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panye. Aunſwere therefore to the ſiſter, whiche aſketh of vs touchinge her eſtate, not with
<pb facs="tcp:26296:10"/> mine, but with the Apoſtles ſentence. <hi>Mulier quae ſub viro eſt, viuente viro, aſtricta eſt leg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>: quòd ſi mortuus fuerit vir eius, liberata eſt á lege viri. Ergo viuente viro, adultera eſt, ſi duxerit alterum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Marke this wel, reader.</note> 
               <hi>Et in alio loco. Mulier alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gata eſt legi quanto tempore vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit vir eius: ſi autem dormierit vir</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. vii.</note> 
               <hi>eius, liberata eſt, cui vult, nubat, tantum in domino. Omnes igitur cauſationes Apoſtolus ampu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans definiuit apertiſsime, viuente viro, a dulteram eſse mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ierem, ſi alteri nupſerit.</hi> That is to ſaye, the woman that is maried, is bounde to the lawe, as longe as her huſbande liueth. But yf her huſbande be dead, ſhe is fre from the lawe of him. She is then a breaker of wedlocke, yf
<pb facs="tcp:26296:11"/> ſhe be maried to another huſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bande, her firſt huſbande being alyue. And in another place S. Paule hath the ſame, affirming that there is no cauſe, but death <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or .vii.</note> onelye, to breake the bonde of mariage. Wherfore the Apoſtle takinge awaye all cauſes, that can bee alleged, determineth moſte plainelye, that the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man committeth aduoutrie, yf ſhe doe marrye another man, her huſbande liuinge. S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Hierom.</note> addeth theſe woordes there. I wyll not that thou brynge for the to me the raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhers violence, the mothers per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſuaſion, the authoritie or ſtyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe of the father, the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of the kin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>folke, the deceite of the ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tours, and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of them, or others, the
<pb facs="tcp:26296:11"/> endomages of the houſholde goodes. <hi>Quam diu viuit vir eius<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> licet adulter ſit, licet Sodomita, licet flagitijs omnibus coopertus, &amp; ab vxore propter haec ſeelera dereli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus, maritus e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us reputatur, cui alterum virum aſciſere non li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet. Nec Apoſtolus haec propria authoritate decernit, ſed Chriſto in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">ii. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iii.</note> 
               <hi>ſe loquente, Chriſti verba ſecutus eſt, qui in euangelio ai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Qui di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. xix.</note> 
               <hi>vxorem ſuam, excepta for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatione, facit eam maechari, et qui dimiſſam accepiret adulter eſt. Animaduerte quid dicat, qui dimiſſam acceperit, adulter eſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iue ipſa dim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſerit virum, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> viro dimiſſa ſit, adulter eſt quieam ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceperit.</hi> As longe as her huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d liueth (ſayeth S. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erom aunſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>weringe to the queſtion before ſpoken of) althoughe he be an
<pb facs="tcp:26296:12"/> aduouterer, althoughe he be a ſynner agaynſt nature, or elles <note place="margin">Note this againſt all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of the Lutherans and Swin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glians.</note> full of all kindes of vices, and be alſo forſaken of his wyfe for theſe ſynnes, he is iudged her huſbande, and ſhe maye not lawfully marrye another, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les he liueth. And the Apoſtle decreed or determined not thys thing of his owne authoritie, but he folowed Chriſtes wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, whiles he ſpake in hym, whiche ſayeth in the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. He that putteth awaye hys wyfe, except it be for aduoutrie, maketh her commit aduoutrie, and he whiche marieth her, that is ſo putte awaye, is an aduouterer. Note well what Chriſte ſayeth. He that recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth her to his wyfe, that is putte awaye from her huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:12"/> is an aduouterer, whether ſhe had forſaken her huſbande, or els her huſbande had forſaken her, he whiche taketh her, com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mitteth aduoutrie. Then S. Hierom making an end of this doubt, in the whiche his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was required. Sayeth: <hi>Ergo &amp; iſta ſoror, quae vt dicit, vim paſſa eſt, vt alteri iungeretur, ſi vult corpus Chriſti ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pere, non adultera repu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ari, agat poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam, ita dumtaxat, vt ſecondo viro, qui maritus appellatur, ſed ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulter eſt, à tempore poenitentiae non copuletur.</hi> Wherefore, let this ſyſter, which, as ſhe ſaieth, was enforced and compelled to marrye vnto an other man, doe penaunce, if ſhee wyll receaue Chriſtes body, and be not cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted an aduoutreſſe, but ſo onely
<pb facs="tcp:26296:13"/> let her doe penaunce, that from the tyme of it, ſhee be no more coupled with the ſeconde man, which is called a huſbande, but he is an aduouterer. Heather to S. Hierom. Is not this mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtlie written in this mattier? What ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is wiſe, wil not be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eue S. Hierom following y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ge for their opinion no ſcripture rightlye taken?</p>
            <p>S. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de our countreye man iudged the ſame, writynge thus: <hi>Nulla cauſa eſt, dei lege</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in Marcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ol. xxx.</note> 
               <hi>praeſcripta, vt viu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nte ea, quae re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licta eſt al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a ducatur.</hi> There is no cauſe written in Gods lawe, <note place="margin">This was wrytten a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue viij. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. yeres paſt.</note> that another wyfe ſhoulde bee maried whiles ſhe liued, which was le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te or forſaken. What madnes was in Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:13"/> Iohn Hoper, and ſuche o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of that ſorte, to teache and def<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de the contrarye to thys doctrine grounded vppon the holye Scriptures, the old god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Doctours, and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels? Is this to refou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igion (as they pretende) to her purenes, whiche they falſely affirme that ſhe had loſt here<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But I wil go forward, for the further confutation of thys opinion.</p>
            <p>Adam by inſpiration of the holye Ghoſt, ſayed of hys wife Eue. <hi>Hoc nunc os ex oſsibus me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is &amp; ce.</hi> Thys bone is of my bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and thys fleaſhe of my fleſhe, for whiche thynge the man ſhall forſake hys father and mother, and he ſhall clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e faſte to his wyfe, and they ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:26296:14"/> be two in one fleſhe. The which wordes declare (as Chriſt wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth) that mariage ought not to be broken for anye cauſe, tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching <note place="margin">Math. xix.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> band &amp; knot of it. Chriſt addeth to theſe wordes of Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſayth: <hi>quod Deus coniunxit, homo no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeparet.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can not or ought not to deuide the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whiche God hathe ioyned together in matrimonye. Then the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees ſayed to Chriſt. Why then did Moyſes bydde the man to geue hys wyfe a byl of diuorſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo to leaue her? He aunſwered to them and ſayed: Moyſes dyd permitte you to forſake youre wyues for the hardnes of your heartes, but it was not ſo at the beginninge. Theſe wordes laſte written (but it was not ſo in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:26296:14"/> of mariage, declare playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye that Chriſt would mariage <note place="margin">Peter ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr ſaieth that God badde them forſake their wiue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or. vii.</note> ſhoulde not be broken for anye cauſe touchinge the bonde of it, although for aduoutrie it were broken concerninge the mans and womans keping together, and the vſe of mariage in ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring the duety one to an other. Moreouer S. Paule ſayeth <note place="margin">Rom. vii.</note> thus. The woman, whiche is vnder the man, or in ſubiection to him: is bounde to the man by the lawe, as longe as he liueth. Yf the man be deade, ſhe is lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the lawe of him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore whiles the man liueth, if ſhe be with an other man, as her huſbande, ſhe ſhalbe iudged a breaker of matrimonie, but if her huſbande were deade, ſhe is free from the lawe of the man,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26296:15"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26296:16"/> ſo that ſhe is no wedlocke brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, though ſhe be with another man, as her huſbande. Thys texte maketh euidently againſt them that ſaye, a man may put awaye his wyfe for aduoutrye &amp; marye an other. For he ſaieth that the wyfe is ſo bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to her huſbande, during hys naturall lyfe, that he beinge yet aliue, if ſhe marie to another man, ſhe breaketh mariage, &amp; ſhe is an ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoutreſſe: he ſayeth not, ſhe is bounde to him by the lawe vntil he committe aduoutrie, but as longe as he liueth. Whiche is to be vnderſtand of the newe law, and of the bonde of mariage of the ſame lawe, whiche can not be loſed vntyl deathe of the one partye, as ſainte Paule affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, <note place="margin">i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or. vii.</note> ſaying againe: The wyfe
<pb facs="tcp:26296:16"/> is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de by the lawe to her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande, as longe as her huſband liueth. Yf her huſbande do ſlepe, that is to ſaye, if he doe dye, ſhe is at libertie, to marye with whome ſhe wyll, onelye in oure lorde, that is, to a Chriſten man and godly. Saint Hierom, ſaint Auſten, ſaint Bede, and manye other greate learned men, and more god<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, Iohan Hoper, and ſuche o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers are, ſoo haue (as it appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth afore) taken theſe places of ſainte Paule, as I haue vſed them here nowe. What can bee moore plainlye ſpoken of ſainte Paule, then this is, againſt Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter Martyr, Iohn Hoper, and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſuche others, that defende the contrarie opinion in thys mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er? Agayne ſaint Paule ſaieth <note place="margin">i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:26296:17"/> vnto them, whiche are maried, I commaunde not but our lord doeth, that the wife departe not <note place="margin">i. Cor. vii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> from her huſbande. Yf ſhe be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated, let her abide vnmarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or let her be reconciled vnto her huſbande againe. And let not the huſbande put away his wyfe from him, excepte it be for aduoutrie (as Chriſte ſayeth) and if he put her awaye for that cauſe, yet let him remayne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>married, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wife muſt neades doe. This mente ſainte Paule, as the letter it ſelfe declareth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly. And alſo ſaint Auſten, <note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rm. dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>onte, cap. xxv xxvi, xxvii.</note> ſaint Hierom, Chryſoſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen, and manye other auncient, and noble clerkes. Paule ment not of a womans departing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her huſbande, for anye lyghter cauſe than for aduoutrye (as
<pb facs="tcp:26296:17"/> Peter Martyr ſayeth falſlye that he did) for that was the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye cauſe whiche Chriſte did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte, and it is not lawefull for any other cauſe, the wyfe to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake her huſbande, and to bee from him, becauſe ſhe is bounde to clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e vnto him, and to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre his duetie to him (as Paule witneſſeth) and not to defraude him of it.</p>
            <p>A cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell called Mileuitane, at the whiche ſaint Auſten was preſent, determined thys con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie, ſayinge. <hi>Placuit ut ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cundum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Cap. xvii.</note> 
               <hi>euangelicam &amp; apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam diſciplinam, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dimiſſus ab uxore, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dimiſſa á marito, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teri coniungatur, ſed ita maneant, aut ſibimet reconcilientur, quod ſi contempſerint, ad poenitentiam re digantur.</hi> It pleaſeth vs, that
<pb facs="tcp:26296:18"/> accordinge to thee learninge or doctrine of the Goſpell, and of <note place="margin">Mat. xix. i. Cor. vii.</note> thapoſtle, nother the huſbande forſaken of his wyfe for aduou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, nor the wyfe, whiche is put awaye of her huſbande for the like crime, be maried to another, but let them ſo remayne vnma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, or be reconciled amongeſt them ſelfes. The whiche lawe or act, if they do or ſhal deſpiſe, let them be broughte to doe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce. Thys was alſo enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of many other counſels, and <note place="margin">Aphricanum cap. lxix.</note> namelye in the counſell holden in Aphrica of. CCxvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. byſhops, at the whiche ſaint Auſten was preſente.</p>
            <p>Origen was of the ſame <note place="margin">Tom, iii. homi, vii, in Matth.</note> minde and iudgemente, when he ſaie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Scio quoſdam qui praeſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> eccleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, extra ſcriptura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> permiſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26296:18"/> ſe aliquam nubere, u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro priori u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uente, &amp; contra ſcripturam quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">i. Cor. vii.</note> 
               <hi>fecerunt, dicentem: Mulier alligata eſt legi, quamdiu uiuit uir eius. Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. vii.</note> 
               <hi>uiuente uiro adultera uocabitur, ſi iuncta fuerit alteri uiro.</hi> I knowe <note place="margin">Idem habet. Auguſ. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i. cap. xii, de co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ingus adultes rinis.</note> that certen rulers of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, haue with out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture ſuffered a woman to marye, her firſt huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de being alyue, &amp; they haue done it, playne agaynſt the ſcriptures, ſaying: A woman is bounde to the lawe, as longe as her huſband lyueth. Alſo Paule ſayeth, the woman ſhalbe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a breaker of wedlocke if ſhee marye an other manne, her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bande being yet a lyue. Hether to Origen, which wrote a bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e thirtene hundreth yeres paſte a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore oure tyme.</p>
            <p>Chriſte mente euen the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:26296:19"/> thinge, ſaying: Who ſoeuer put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth awaye his wyfe, excepte it <note place="margin">Mat. 5. &amp;. 19.</note> be for her aduoutrie, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth another wyfe, he breaketh mariage, and committeth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutrie. And he whiche marieth her ſo put awaye for aduoutrie, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitteth aduoutrie. For Chriſt teacheth vs here three leeſſons. The firſte is, that a man maye <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a.</note> not lawfullye put awaye hys wyfe, and that concerning bed and bourde onelye, but for her aduoutrie onelye, and for no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſe at all. The ſeconde is <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that if he forſake his wyfe for aduoutrie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted of her, than he maye not marrye agayne, as longe as ſhe lyueth: as ſainte <note place="margin">i. Cor. vii. Rom. vii.</note> Paule intreatynge of the ſame mattier witneſſeth playnlye. The thirde leſſon is, that who <note place="margin">iii.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:26296:19"/> ſoeuer marieth a woman diuor ſed from her huſbande, for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutrie, he committeth aduou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, becauſe he marrieth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mans wife, for the band of mariage remaineth ſtyll, and ſhall as longe as bothe parties lyue. Theſe thre thinges are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly agaynſt the beleife of the Phariſies, which thought that it was lawfull for them to put awaye their wyues for euerye lighte cauſe, and to marrye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, and that he committed not aduoutrie, whiche married a woman ſo put away from her huſbande. S. Auſten aunſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to an argument made vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſtes wordes, after this <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. vi, lib. ii. cap. viii. de ad ulterinis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. cap. x. xi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> maner. Who ſo euer putteth awaye hys wyfe, but for ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoutrie, and marrieth another
<pb facs="tcp:26296:20"/> breaketh matrimonie, <hi>ergo,</hi> he that putteth awaye his wyfe for aduoutrie, and marieth an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, breaketh not matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye. To this reaſon S. Auſten (I ſaid) anſwereth refuting it, by another like made vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſ. Ia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes wordes, ſayinge: <hi>ſcienti bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num et non facienti peccatum eſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iaco. iiii.</note> 
               <hi>illi.</hi> He ſinneth that knoweth what is good, and doeth it not. Thys argument made of the contrarie ſenſe, <hi>ergo,</hi> he ſinneth not, that knoweth not what is good, is nought: Becauſe a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſynneth through ignoraunce as Chriſt witneſſeth. Wherefore Chriſte ment that he ſynneth <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. xii.</note> more greuouſlye, whiche put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth awaye his wife without aduoutrie, and marieth ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, than he doeth, whiche put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb facs="tcp:26296:20"/> her awaye for aduoutrie, and marieth agayne, lyke as he ſinneth more that ſinneth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e, than he which ſynneth ignorauntly, and yet both doth offende God. This S. Auſten <note place="margin">Lib. 2. cap. 10, de adulter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> coniug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is.</note> gathereth verye godly and ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedlye out of the Euangelie of Marke and Luke, whiche as it were, expoundinge Matthew, affirme abſolutlye, that who ſoeuer for anye cauſe, putteth awaye his wife, and marieth another, committeth aduoutrie in ſo doynge.</p>
            <p>S. Auſten confirmeth thys <note place="margin">Lib. de bono co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> iugali. cap. 3.</note> ſaying when he expounded S. Paules ſentence to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines aboue recited. <hi>Confae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derationem maris &amp; feminae. &amp;c.</hi> The ſcripture ſo doeth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend the ioyninge together of man &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:26296:21"/> man in mariage. That it is not lawfull to the woman to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie agayne another man as longe as her huſbande liueth, nor the man maye marye an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wife, as long as his wyfe deuorſed for her aduoutrye ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth. <hi>Interuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te deuortio, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deratio illa non aboletur nuptialis, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a vt ſibi coniuges ſint etiam ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>parati, cum illis autem adulterium committant, cum quibus fuerint poſt ſuum repudium copulati.</hi> The co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ioyning together of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage is not aboliſhed or taken awaye throughe di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orcement betwene the man &amp; woman, in ſo muche as that they are man &amp; wife, yea when they are ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated. For they doe committe aduoutrie with them, whome they haue maried, ſynce theyr
<pb facs="tcp:26296:21"/> diuorcement.</p>
            <p>S. Auſten hathe agayne, <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel autem initum connubium in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib de beno ee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugali cap. xv.</note> 
               <hi>ciuitate deinoſtri, vbi etiam expri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ma duorum hominum copula, quoddam ſacramentum nuptiae ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap> quod nullo modo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i alicuius eorum morte, diſſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> The marryage once entred or begonne in the citie of oure. GOD, where, yea of the firſt couplynge together of man and woman, the mariage beareth a certaine ſacrament, or a ſigne of a holye thynge, whiche bande can not be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done but by deathe of one of <note place="margin">Tom. vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nuptiis. ca. x. li. 2. ca. 13. de com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is adulter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de ſerm, dei in monte. ca 25<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> them. He holdeth in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his workes many feſtlye, that death onely of the man, or of the woman, and no other thinge or cauſe, diſſolueth and
<pb facs="tcp:26296:22"/> breaketh matrimonie once per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited through carnall dealynge, excepte they conſent to vowe chaſtitie.</p>
            <p>Innocentius the fyrſt Pope of that name, whiche was in <note place="margin">Libro decreto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſuorum cap. vi.</note> S. Auſtens time hath the ſame. Wherefore we ſee euidentlye, that Peter Martyr, and Iohn Hoper, whiche was a white monke, and ſuche others erred ſhamefullye, when they dyd teache, preache, and ſette forth the contrarye vnto thys doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine grounded vpon the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the counſails, and olde Doctours of the churche. But of this queſtion lette this be ſayed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:26296:22"/>
            <head>The ſecond Chapter.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>A confutation of an abhominable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure of Peter Martyrs ſettynge furth, which Willia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Tyndale taught in his preface vpon the Epiſtle to the Romaines before his tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, which is that our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth only in god, and nothinge in vs, whiche wicked opinion taketh cleane away mans fre wyll from hym.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THys great Prophet of oure newe brethren, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt many other de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſtable opinions and ſayinges whiche he hath in his commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries written vpon the fyrſte Epiſtle to the Corynthians, thus he ſetteth furth. <hi>Eſt prorſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> vt noſtra, ita liberotum noſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſalus ex mera dei electione,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:23"/> et miſericordia, &amp;c.</hi> Bothe oure ſaluation, and our childrens al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is vtterlye of the onely elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and mercie of God.</p>
            <p>Agayn he affirmeth the ſame with theſe wordes. <hi>Tantum ex</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. ix.</note> 
               <hi>dei gratia at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> electione, ſiue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſione (ut dicit Paulus: Non om</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. clxxvi.</note> 
               <hi>nes, qui ſunt ex Iſrael et c.) Noſtra ſalus conſtat.</hi> Oure ſaluation co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth onely (ſayeth he) of or by the grace of God, &amp; his election or promes, as S. Paule ſaieth. All that are of Iſraell &amp;c. Is not this a perillous doctrine, and a peſtilent errour, whiche Wylliam Tyndall taught in his preface vppon the Epiſtle to the Romaynes, and one Barnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyne, an Italian in his booke written in the Italia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tongue, &amp; tranſlated in to Engliſhe by a
<pb facs="tcp:26296:23"/> younge gentle woman. This o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion is not onelye agaynſte mans free wyll, but alſo againſt manye euidente places of the ſcripture. For if oure ſaluation ſtandeth onelye in Gods electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Gods promiſſe, mercye, and grace: than it conſiſteth not in anye worke of man, not in the hearinge of Goddes worde, not in his faieth, not in hys repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, or penaunce, not in hys prayinge to God for the pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſinge of it, not in geuinge of <note place="margin">Faith onely doth not i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſtifie man.</note> almes, not in faſtinge, not in his fiaunce to God or hope of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not in the receauing of bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme, not in the dreade of God, not in charitee, finallie not in good workes, whiche all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are maniſtly againſt Gods holye worde. For touchinge the
<pb facs="tcp:26296:24"/> firſt, Peter ſaied: Thou haſt, O Lorde wordes of euerlaſtynge life. Paule ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed: I haue ſhowed <note place="margin">i. Cor. xv.</note> to you the Euangel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, thorowe the whiche ye are ſaued. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto agreeth, that he ſayeth: I am not a ſhamed of the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelie, for it is the power of God <note place="margin">Rom. x.</note> to the ſaluation of euery man, that beleueth. Agayne he affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the ſame thinge ſayinge: Thys worde is the worde of fayeth, whiche we doe preache, For if thou confeſſe with thye mouthe that Ieſus is our lord, and beleue with thy heart, that God raiſed vp him from death, thou ſhalt be ſaued. <hi>Corde enim</hi> 
               <note place="margin">With his hart, that is to ſay, frely and volen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarilie.</note> 
               <hi>creditur ad iuſtitiam, ore fit confeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſio ad ſalutem.</hi> For a man dothe beleue with his hart, to receaue righteouſneſſe, and confeſſeth
<pb facs="tcp:26296:24"/> with his mouth to obtayne ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. What can be more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſayd againſt this erronious <note place="margin">Reade ye, that do th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. Peter Martyr is a greate clerke.</note> opinion? For affirmeth he not here manifeſtlye that we do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eue with oure hearte to pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe our iuſtification<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and with our mouthe confeſſe or acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge Chriſte, and his trueth, that we maye be ſaued? Is it then true, that oure ſaluation dependeth onlye vpon Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, promiſſe, grace, &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Dependeth it not vpon oure faieth, and confeſſion of it, and of Chriſte? Howe often tymes <note place="margin">Mat. xv. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. x. Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. vii. Ephe. ii.</note> ſayed Chriſt: Thy fayeth hathe ſaued the? Sayeth not alſoo Paule: Ye are ſaued by grace thorowe faieth. Manye tymes Peter Martyr affirmeth that onelye faieth doth iuſtifie man,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:25"/> and ſaue him: &amp; nowe he ſayeth that his ſaluation co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye in Gods election, promiſſe, mercye, and grace. What diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greinge is thys with himſelfe? Is it anye meruaile that he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth not with vs, Whiche a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth not with him ſelfe, what mad men are they, that wyll yet folowe his vngodlye opinions, when he erreth thus playnly, &amp; ſo ſhamefully againſt the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures? Dauid ſayeth: Thou, o <note place="margin">Pſal. xvi. Pſal. xxxvi. Pſal. xxxi.</note> Lorde, ſaueſt them, that truſte or hope in the: And God ſaueth them whiche haue their affi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce in him: And they ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne mercye of God, which doe truſte in him. S. Paule ſayeth, that Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did beleue againſt hope vnder hope to be iuſtified, and ſaulued, and that hope is
<pb facs="tcp:26296:25"/> the helmet of ſaluation, and yet <note place="margin">Ephe. vi.</note> Peter Martyr was not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to ſaye that oure ſaluation ſtandeth onelye vpon God. Chriſte ſayed, who ſoeuer bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, and is baptiſed, ſhalbe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marci. V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>imo.</hi> Tit. iii.</note> Sainte Paule witneſſeth that God ſaued vs by his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, thorowe baptiſme. And S. Peter affirmeth alſo, that bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme ſaueth vs, &amp; Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr ſayeth that oure ſaluation commeth onlye of God. O igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rant <note place="margin">Baptiſme is not ama<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e onelye of our iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, but a cauſe of it.</note> man: he ſaieth that onelye faieth ſaueth vs, and that bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is but a ſigne, marke, or ſeale of oure iuſtification, and ſaluation. But Chriſte, ſainte Paule, &amp; ſainte Peter, affirme that we are ſaued by baptiſme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> What follie is it then to geue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>redence to Peter Martyr, or
<pb facs="tcp:26296:26"/> to anye other of that ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te, the Swinglians, and Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, which are deceaued af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſemblable maner.</p>
            <p>Dauid prayed to God, that <note place="margin">Prayer ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vs. Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xxxv.</note> he might be ſaued, ſaying: <hi>Saluu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me fac deus meus ſperantem in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi> Saue me, o my God, whiche do truſte in the. Is this our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to depende only vpon God? Howe blynde are they, whiche ſaye, that Peter Martyr was a ſinguler learned man in diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitee, and that his commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries are verye learned lie made? Hathe not affection blynded them? But heare further the Prophete I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell ſayeth. <note place="margin">Ioelis. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. We obtain oure ſalua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er and by not fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth onl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Who ſoeuer ſhall call vpon thee name of God, ſhalbe ſaued: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claringe therby, that our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion conſiſteth in prayer: and
<pb facs="tcp:26296:26"/> Peter Martyr, Wylliam Tyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall, and the Italian Barnar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine, ſay, that it is onlye in God, and nothinge in vs, nor in oure doinges. God ſaieth by his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet. <hi>Conuertiminiad me, &amp; ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iſaye. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v. We are ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned by pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce, and not by faith onelye. i. Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>eritis oe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s fines terrae.</hi> Tourne ye to me, all the coaſtes of the earth, &amp; ye ſhalbe ſaued. Saint Paule ſayeth that repentaunce worketh in vs oure ſaluation. Howe ignoraunte are theſe men then?</p>
            <p>Zacheus promiſed to Chriſt <note place="margin">Luc. xix. Wee are iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtified by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, &amp; not by faieth onlye.</note> to geue halfe of his riches to the poore, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d if he hadde done wronge to anye man, to reſtore to him foure tymes ſo muche. Than Chriſte ſayd. <hi>Hodie ſalus facta eſt huic domui, quia &amp; hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> filius Abrahe eſt.</hi> Thys daye, health or ſaluation is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men to
<pb facs="tcp:26296:27"/> this houſe, becauſe he is alſoo the chyld or ſonne of Abraham. Whiche oure ſauiours wordes, declare that we are ſaued by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring of goodes gotten wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, &amp; by almes, &amp; not by onely faith, &amp; that our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth not only in god, as Pe. Martyr moſt falſely ſaieth that it doeth.</p>
            <p>Ionas the Prophet ſaied. <hi>Quaecun <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> uoui, reddam proſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute mea domino.</hi> I wyll rendre <note place="margin">Uowes.</note> to oure Lorde for my ſaluation, euerye thinge, that I haue vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed. But Peter Martyr ſayed oure ſaluation conſiſteth onelye in God, &amp; that no man is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to perfourme hys vowe made vnto God, that he maye be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. One of the cauſes of thys his erroure, was that he was a Chanon of ſaint Auſtens ordre
<pb facs="tcp:26296:27"/> and yet married a wyfe, not withſtandynge he had vowed chaſtitie. And God requireth of <note place="margin">Pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xxv.</note> vs the perfourmau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vowes, as the holie ſcripture <note place="margin">Eccle. v.</note> witneſſeth playnelye.</p>
            <p>The prophete ſayed I wyll ſhew to the, o man, what thing <note place="margin">Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. vi.</note> is good, and what oure Lorde doth require of the. Truelye, to doe right or iuſtice, to loue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and with care to walke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, that is, to ſerue him diligentlye. This is the voice of our lorde to the citie. <hi>Et ſalus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">We are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the feare of god</note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rit timentibus nomen eius.</hi> And healthe, or ſaluation ſhalbe to them whiche feare his name. Is this our ſaluation to confiſt onlye in faieth, or in God onely?</p>
            <p>Malachie the prophet trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <note place="margin">malach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of Chriſtes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, ſaieth.
<pb facs="tcp:26296:28"/> And the ſonne of righteouſneſſe ſhall ryſe vnto you, that feare my name, and ſaluation in his fethers. Zacharie ſaied by the inſpiration of the holie ghoſte: <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> His mercie ſhalbe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> progenie to progenie, vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that feare his name. Salomon ſaied. <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor domini fons ui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> The dread <note place="margin">Prou. xiiii.</note> of oure lorde, is a fountayne of lyfe. Agayne, feare putteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye ſinne. Was not then Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Martyr plainlie ignorant, to ſaye, that oure ſaluation ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth onelye in God, or that one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye <note place="margin">Fayth doth not only i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie vs.</note> faieth is the meane to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayne of God oure iuſtification and ſaluation? S. Paule ſaieth <note place="margin">Gala. v.</note> that, that faieth auaileth, which doeth worke by charitee, and that with oute charitee, faieth can not ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e vs. He alſo ſayeth,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:28"/> the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe ſaued thorow <note place="margin">i. Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> bearing of children, if ſhe do con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinue in faieth, charitee, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes with ſobriete. Alſo he ſaid vnto Timothe the byſhop. <note place="margin">i. Tim. iiii.</note> Take hede to thy ſelfe, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to learninge, or teachinge of the people, and continue therin. For if thou ſo doe, thou ſhalte ſaue thy ſelfe, and them, that heare thee. Brieflye, he ſaieth. Worke ye youre owne ſaluation with feare and tremblinge. O howe blinde then was Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr to ſaye, that oure ſaluation conſiſteth onelye in God, or in faieth alone, and not in vs, and the workes of oure freewyll, aidid of God by hys eſpeciall grace? But I wyll make nowe an ende of this trai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te, and in an other booke ſet furth dyuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:26296:29"/> ſhamefull errours, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable hereſies of this man, and of ſome others alſo. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer Peter Martyr ſaieth. <hi>Ilico ut quis credit, &amp; ſalutem habet, &amp; iuſtificatur.</hi> Strayghte after a man beleueth, he is boeth ſaued, and alſo iuſtified. Whiche hys ſayinge is clearlye agaynſte the ſcriptures alleadged in the laſte chapiter, and theſe alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Miſerere mei deus etc.</hi> Haue mercie vpon me o God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge <note place="margin">Pſalm. I.</note> to thy great mercye, and after the multitude of thye mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyfull workes, put thou awaye mine iniquitie. Who can denye but Dauid the prophet beleued when he thus praied, ſeeing S. Paule witneſſeth, that no man <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. x.</note> can praye or call vpon God for remiſſion of his ſinnes, and hys
<pb facs="tcp:26296:29"/> ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, except he beleue afore, and yet Dauid was not incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinente iuſtified and ſaued.</p>
            <p>Saieth not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prophet Ioel, that whoſoeuer ſhall call vpon thee <note place="margin">Ioel. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> name of GOD ſhalbe ſaued? Whiche ſayinge proueth that a man muſte neades firſte beleue in Chriſt, before he can be ſaued thorowe his prayer. The ſame thing, appeareth moſt euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, by the Publican, that bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <note place="margin">Luc. xix.</note> before he went into the tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple to praye, for to pourchaſe his iuſtification and ſaluation throughe hys calling vpon God to haue mercye vpon hym.</p>
            <p>Dyd not the Iewes beleue when S. Peter badde them <note place="margin">Act. ii. &amp;. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> tourne to God, to repent, and to be baptized, that they might obtayne their iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
<pb facs="tcp:26296:30"/> of their ſinnes? Sayeth not Paule alſo, let vs go with an affiaunce, hope, or boldnes, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eb. iiii.</note> vnto the ſeate of Godes grace, that we maye receyue mercie, and finde grace for our helpe in due ſeaſon? Who ſeeth not then that we muſt nedes beleue, and put our affiaunce and truſte in God, to obtayne of hym mercye and grace, through our praiers, afore we doe praye to him ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? Sayd not likewiſe Chriſt: <hi>Quecumque petieritis in oratione credentes, accipietis.</hi> What thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges <note place="margin">Math. xxi.</note> ſo euer ye ſhall aſke in your prayers, ye ſhall haue them, yf ye doe beleue. S. Iames ſaieth that we muſt aſke in faythe, yf <note place="margin">Iaco. i.</note> we wyll obtayne our petition. Muſte we not then haue fyrſte a beleife in God, &amp; a confidence
<pb facs="tcp:26296:30"/> or hope to obtayn our petition, when we deſier of God to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geue vs our treſpaſſes, &amp; to ſaue vs, and than after through our prayers, and repentaunce pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe thoſe benefites of hym? S. Auſten ſayeth in many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his bookes. <hi>Fides primum datur, ut caetera impetrentur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fayth is firſt of al geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that other thynges neceſſarie for his ſaluation, may be gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through it. But this is ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> confutaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this groſſe &amp; perilous error taught of Peter Martyr. Nowe I wyll refute and improue another abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable hereſie of his, whiche he defendeth in his commentaries <note place="margin">Fol, 273<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> vpon the fyrſte Epiſtle to the Corinthians. And it is of the baptiſynge of children, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:26296:31"/> he defendeth to be ſaued, if they were neuer baptiſed, but depar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted without baptiſme.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>The. iii. Chapter.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The baptiſme of children, againſt all the Swinglians, and not Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter Martyr o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ely, and the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aptiſtes.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ayn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Auſten in this matter <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or. 7. Fol. 173. et 174. 175. 176.</note> is manifeſtlye agaynſt Peter Martyr, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che defendeth in his commen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taries <note place="margin">He made baptiſme but a ſigne or a marke of our iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. fol. 177, &amp;, 178.</note> vpon the Corinthians, that a chriſtian mans chylde hath remiſſion of his ſynne, and the ſpirite of God, before he be baptiſed, and ſhalbe ſaued al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb facs="tcp:26296:31"/> he were neuer baptiſed. Whiche doctrine is agaynſt the ſcriptures, and al the olde doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours ſayinges, and not onelye agaynſt theſe ſentences folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge. <hi>In paruulis gratia Dei per</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aug. lib. i. cap xxxix. de pecc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orum et <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>baptiſmum eius qui veni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudine carnis p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, id agitur, vt euacuet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r caro peccati.</hi> That thinge is done by the grace of <note place="margin">Reade you that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyr ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> muche.</note> God, throughe the baptiſme of hym, whiche came in the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſynneful fleaſhe, that the fleaſhe of ſynne ſhoulde be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a waye.</p>
            <p>Item he ſayeth, becauſe S. Paule affirmeth that through <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſtol lxxxix.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. v.</note> one mans ſynne (Adam) all were condemned, the baptiſme of children is not ſuperfluous, for aſmuch as they which were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned throughe their byrthe,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:32"/> ſhoulde be deliuered from that condemnation throughe baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me. Agayne he ſayeth. <hi>Poteſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. i. cap. xvi. de peccatorum.</note> 
               <hi>recte di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i paruulos ſine baptiſmo de corpore exeuntes, in damnatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne omnium mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſſima futuros. Multum enim fallit &amp; fallitur, qui eos in damnatione praedicat non futuros.</hi> It maye be well ſayed, that the children whiche do die <note place="margin">Than Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Martyr deceaued men, and he him ſelfe was muche deceaued.</note> withoute baptiſme ſhall be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moſte eaſie damnation of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. He is much deceiued him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe, and no leſſe deceyueth other, whiche ſayeth that they ſhall not be damned. Alſo he ſaith. <hi>Periturus erat paruulus, nec habiturus vitam aeternam, ſi per</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. xxxiii. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>peccatorum.</note> 
               <hi>ſacramentum baptiſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret in vnigenitum filium.</hi> The childe ſhould haue periſhed, and not haue had euerlaſtynge life,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:32"/> yf he had not beleued throughe the ſacrament of baptiſme, in the only begotten ſonne of god.</p>
            <p>Item vpon theſe wordes of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib. i. cap. 27. de peccatorum.</hi> Ioan. iii.</note> S. Iohn, he that hathe the ſon, hath euerlaſtinge life. <hi>Non igi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur regnum caelorum, ſed nec vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aeternam habebunt paruuli, ſi filiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non habebunt, quem niſi per bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmum habere non poſſunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therfore younge children ſhall not haue the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, <note place="margin">Tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Peter Martyr <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and ſo do all that follow him.</note> nor yet euerlaſtinge lyfe, yf thei haue not the ſonne of God (Chriſte) whiche they can not haue, but by baptiſme.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Omnino in remiſſionem peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum baptizantur et paruuli, alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin non habebunt in regno celo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum uitam.</hi> Younge children are <note place="margin">Lib. v. Hypo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> baptiſed vtterlye for to obtaine remiſſion of their ſinnes, or els
<pb facs="tcp:26296:33"/> they ſhal not haue life in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Likewiſe in the ſame boke he ſaieth. <hi>Paruulo niſi baptiſ mi gratia ſubuenerit, diſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riet de populo ſuo.</hi> If the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment of baptiſme ſhall not help the infante, he ſhall not be ſaued <note place="margin">Tom. iii. lib. i. cap. xxiii. de. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c.</note> with other folke. Againe he wri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth. <hi>Nulla ex noſtro arbitrio, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> baptiſmum Chriſti ſalus eterna promittatur infantibus, quam non promitti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſcriptura, omnibus huma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nis inge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>s preferenda.</hi> Let not eternall ſaluation be promiſed to infantes, after our own will, without the baptiſme of chriſt, whiche ſaluation the ſcripture, which ought to be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all mennes wyttes, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <note place="margin">Aug. Tom. ii. Epiſt. xxviii. et lib. de origine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ae cap. xviii. &amp; xxi.</note> not to them. In an other place thus he ſaieth. <hi>Quiſquis dixerit, quòd in Chriſto uiuificabu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tur etiam paruuli, qui ſine ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti
<pb facs="tcp:26296:33"/> eius participatione de hac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uita exeunt, hic profecto &amp; co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tra apoſtolicam praedicationem uenit, &amp; totam condemnat eccleſiam. V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi propterea cum baptizandis par uulis feſtinatur, &amp; curritur, quia ſine dubio creditur eos aliter in chriſto uiuificari non poſse. Qui autem no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> uiuificatur in Chriſto, reſtat ut in eadem condemnatione maneat, de qua dicit apoſtolus, per unius</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. v.</note> 
               <hi>delictum in omnes homines in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demnationem.</hi> Whoſoeuer ſhall ſaye, yea that children ſhalbe made aliue in chriſt (ſpiritually) whiche doe departe out of this lyfe, without any partaking of Chriſtes ſacramente of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, he without doubte doeth bothe againſte S. Paules prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chinge, and alſo he condemneth the whole churche. When men
<pb facs="tcp:26296:34"/> and women therfore, doe haſte and runne to haue their childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> baptized, bycauſe they without doubte beleue, that other wyſe they can not be made alyue in Chriſte, but he that is not made aliue in or by Chriſte, it reſteth that he abydeth ſtill in the ſame damnation of the whiche the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeketh ſaying: Through <note place="margin">Rom. v.</note> one mannes ſinne iudgemente came vpon all men to their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. Who ſeeth not now that Peter Martyr, and hys diſciples erre manifeſtly in this matter, &amp; ought not therfore to be beleued in other their naugh tie opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. <hi>Infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes à peceato ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginis</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aug. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>piſt. 89.</note> 
               <hi>immunes eſse non poſsun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, niſi ab eius reatu per Chriſti bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſma reſoluantur.</hi> Younge chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren can not be without origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb facs="tcp:26296:34"/> ſinne, excepte they be abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from it, by the baptiſme of Chriſte. <hi>Noli credere, noli dicere,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. iii. cap. ix. ai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>a et <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius orig. ad Vincentiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
               <hi>noli docere, infantes antequàm baptiz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntur morte preuentos, poſſe ad originalium peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum indulgentiam peruen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re: ſi uis eſse catholicus.</hi> Beleue not ſayeth ſaint Auſten, ſaye not, teache not, that infantes whiche <note place="margin">The Peter Martyr was not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke. <hi>Lib. iii. car. xii de pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>catorum.</hi>
               </note> depart before they maye be bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſed, can haue forgeueneſſe of their ſinnes, if thou wilt be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke. <hi>Nec paruuli de quibus l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bet ſanctis iuſtis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> procreati, ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginalis peccatireatu abſoluu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, niſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> chriſto fuerint baptizati, pro qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>busta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to impenſius loqui debemus, quanto pro ſe ipſis minus poſsu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> Younge chyldren that be borne of neuer ſo holye and righteous parentes, are not abſolued from
<pb facs="tcp:26296:35"/> originall ſinne, excepte they be <note place="margin">Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyr teacheth the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie</note> baptized in Chriſt, for whom ſo muche the moore we oughte to ſpeake, bycauſe they canne not ſpeake for them ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nos dicimus, aliter infantes ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutem</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Aug. To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. x. Serm. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iii. de v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; uita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eternam non habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros, niſi baptizentur in Chr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſto.</hi> We ſaye, that younge chyldren ſhall not haue otherwyſe ſalua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion and life euerlaſtinge, except they be baptized in Chriſte. <hi>Par uulus non baptizatus pergit in da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Apoſtoli enim ſunt uerba: Ex uno &amp;c. Et dominieſt ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. v. Ioan. iii. <hi>Lib. de g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne. x. cap. xliiii. Lege, Aug<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>07. 157. 90. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>niſi quis renatus fuerit &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> reſiſtit, niſi non chriſtianus.</hi> The younge childe not chriſtened go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into damnation. For Paule ſayth: Throughe one mans ſyn all are damned, and oure lorde ſayeth. Excepte a man be borne
<pb facs="tcp:26296:35"/> agayne of the holye ghoſte, and <note place="margin">Tract. xxxviii. in Ioa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ram <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. x. cap. xiiii. ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. de te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>v.</note> water, he can not enter into heauen. The whiche thinge, no man agayne ſaieth, but he that is no chriſten man. Howe blinde is then Peter Martyr to ſaye that a chriſten mans chylde is iuſtified, before it be borne a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> chriſtened, and that it ſhal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ued if it were not chriſten <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> membred he not, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſaint Paule ſayeth: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 paragraph">
                     <desc>〈1 paragraph〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> borne originallye the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Gods wrathe, and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> anye perſon whiche is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> throughe Adams offe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Paule witneſſeth all m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be made alyue, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> owne faieth in Chriſt, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſayeth of his God fathers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the church, applied to him by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ament of faieth (baptiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26296:36"/> Saint Auſten teſtifieth euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie in ſondrie places of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, <note place="margin">Lib. i. cap. xii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. contra duos. Pelag. Lib. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. peccat. cap. xxvii.</note> that original ſinne hurteth al children, not yet baptized, and that they are not gotten of chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten parents, in that, that their parents are baptized, whiche thinge toucheth the ſoule, but in that, that they are men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, they are begotten &amp; borne in ſinne, and ſhalbe damned for euer, excepte they be throughe baptiſme borne agayne the ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God.</p>
            <p>Sainte Cyprian was of the ſame belefe, ſaying: <hi>Ad remiſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. 3. epiſt. 8. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dum.</note> 
               <hi>peccatorum accipiendam ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ipſo facilius ad baptiſma accedit, quód illi remittantur, non propria, ſed aliena peccata.</hi> The younge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hylde commeth to baptiſme ſo muche the more eaſly to receaue
<pb facs="tcp:26296:36"/> remiſſion of his ſinnes, becauſe <note place="margin">Originall ſinne came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Adam.</note> an other mans ſinne &amp; not hys owne is there forgeuen hym. Peter Martyr defendeth that the chylde hath remiſſion of his ſinne, be fore he be baptized. Oh blindnes of the man, and of his ſcholers.</p>
            <p>Sainte Ambroſe is of the ſame iudgemente ſayinge. <hi>Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib 2. cap. 8. de vocatione gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium.</note> 
               <hi>credi fas eſt, eo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, qui reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nerationis non adepti ſunt ſacramentum, ad ullu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beatorum peruenire conſorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, ueruntamen quare tanta infan tium multitud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, non regenerato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, á perpetua alienatur ſalute, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conturbabitur cor noſtrum, ſi fir</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Read ye Swing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrians.</note> 
               <hi>ma &amp; ſtabili fide omne iudicium dei iuſtum eſse credamus, nec ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petamus habere cognitum, quod uoluit eſse ſecretum, ut ubi in ueſti gari non poteſt, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re ita i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et
<pb facs="tcp:26296:37"/> ſufficiat ſcire quis iudicet &amp; ce.</hi> Yt is not lawefull to be beleued, that they whiche are not bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, do go to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But yet, we neade not to trouble our ſelues to thinke, whye ſo great a num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of babes vnchriſtened ſhuld not be ſaued, if we doe ſurelye and ſtedfaſtlye beleue, that all Gods iudgementes he righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and deſire not to knowe that thinge, whiche God would haue ſecrete, that where it can not be ſearched out, why he doth ſo iudge, it ſhoulde be ſufficient, to knowe who iudgeth.</p>
            <p>Saint Gregorie Nazianzene, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> ſaint Hieroms maiſter, ſayeth. <hi>Melius eſt infantes, ſi pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>culum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquod imminet, non dum rationis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>potes ſanctificare, quàm non ſig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>natos, &amp; initiatos uita excid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26296:37"/>
            <p>It is better that younge chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, whiche haue not yet the vſage of reaſon, be made ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye (through baptiſme) if ther be anye daunger at hande, rather than they ſhoulde looſe euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge lyfe, being not chriſtened, before they doe departe oute of this lyfe.</p>
            <p>Sainte Auſten woulde, that <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. xvi, ſer. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> de temp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re.</note> baptiſme of chyldren ſhould not be differred, but be miniſtred to them, as ſone as they are borne. Alſo he ſaieth that ſaint Cypr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, not makinge a newe decree <note place="margin">Lib. iii. epi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lib. i. ca. xx, de origine ai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Hieron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of it, but kepinge the moſt ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt faieth of the churche, to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte them, whiche iudged that the chylde ſhoulde not be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, before theight daye of hys birthe: ſaied, that the ſoule, not the bodye, ſhoulde periſhe, if he
<pb facs="tcp:26296:38"/> were not baptiſed, and he with other byſhoppes thought, that the chylde ſtreighte after hys birthe mighte be well baptiſed. Sainte Hierome confirmeth this belefe, ſaying. <hi>Infantuli bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiza<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. dialogoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> contra Pelag. Ad latu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> idem</note> 
               <hi>ut eis peccata in baptiſmate dimittantur.</hi> Younge chyldren are baptized, that their ſinnes maye be forgeuen by it. What can Peter Martyr and his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples ſaye to this? Wyll they haue vs beleue them before the ſcriptures, and the olde godlye doctours of Chriſtes churche? What blyndnes is this? Oure lorde of his tendre and greate mercie open their eyes, that they may ſee the trueth of his word, &amp; ſeing it, recule and retourn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> catholyke churche, out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can be ſaued.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:26296:38"/>
            <p>Origen beleued euen as theſe other fathers did, part of whoſe ſentences are nowe recited, for <note place="margin">Hom. xiiii. in Lucam,</note> he ſaith thus, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe wordes of Iob. No man is cleane from the filthyneſſe of ſinne, no al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe hys lyfe were but of one daye vpon the earth. <hi>Et quia</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ca. 25. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 70</note> 
               <hi>per baptiſmi ſacramentum natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis ſordes deponuntur, propterea baptizantur &amp; paruuli. Niſi enim quis renatus fuerit &amp;c.</hi> Becauſe the filthynes of mans naturall birthe is put away thorowe the ſacrament of baptiſme, children are for that cauſe alſo baptiſed. For excepte a man be borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne of water, and the holye <note place="margin">Ioan. iii.</note> ghoſte, he can not entre in to the kingdome of heauen. Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius the firſt, which was in S. Auſtens tyme, and to whome he
<pb facs="tcp:26296:39"/> wrote, holdeth the ſame bele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, ſaying, as ſaint Auſten re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>teth <hi>Lib. ij. cap. iiij. contra duas epiſt,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ripta <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> uita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>m.</note> 
               <hi>pelagiorum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Illudu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro. quod e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> veſtra fraternitas aſserit predicare, paruulos a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ternae uitae praemijs, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam ſine baptiſmatis gratia poſse donari, perfatuum eſt.</hi> It is a verie fooliſhe thing, that thei do preache (as youre brotherhoode affirmeth) that chyldren ſhould be ſaued withoute baptiſme. It appeareth then nowe moſte playne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye howe this opinion, whiche Peter Martyr, folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge the Swinglia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, hathe taughte, to defende that onelye fayth iuſtifieth man, is againſt the holy worde of God, and the holye doctours bothe of the Greke churche<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and alſo of the Latyue, and thereby it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb facs="tcp:26296:39"/> that Peter Martyr, and his ſcolers are not membres of the catholike churche, but ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiques. I beſeche God of hys gracious goodnes tourne their heartes, that they maye imbrace the trueth agayne, and continue therin to hys ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glorie, and their own ſaluation. But heare once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne Origen, whiche was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout. M. thre hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred yeres paſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed, <note place="margin">Orig. lib. vi. Coment. in ca. vi. ad Rom.</note> and writeth after this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: <hi>Pro hoc, ſcilicet corpore pec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cati abolendo, &amp; eccleſia ab apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolis traditionem ſuſcepit etiam paruulis baptiſma dare. Sciebant enim illi, quibus myſteriorum ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creta commiſſa ſunt diuinorum, quod eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent in omnibus ſordes pecc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enuinae, quae peraqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſpiritum ablui deberent.</hi> That is
<pb facs="tcp:26296:40"/> to ſaye. For this bodie of ſinne to be defaced or put awaye, the <note place="margin">An vnwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten veritee of our beleif</note> churche hathe receyued alſo a tradition of the Apoſtles, to geue baptiſme, yea, to children. For they, to whome the ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Goddes myſteries were committed, dyd knowe that there ſhoulde be in all men na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall fylthines of ſynne, which oughte to be waſhed awaye through water &amp; the holy ghoſt This authoritie is againſte Peter Martyr, the authours of the articles annexed vnto the Catechiſme ſette furthe in kinge Edwarde the vi. tyme, and all them, that ſaye eyther that childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not baptiſed ſhulde be ſaued, or that baptiſme is no cauſe of oure iuſtification, but fayth onely, or that baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me
<pb facs="tcp:26296:40"/> is but a ſigne or marke of our iuſtification, or finally that the baptiſme of children is ſet furthe in the Scripture, where it is lefte to the churche by the holy Apoſtles without writing only by traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as Orige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here <note place="margin">De eccleſ. Hierar, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, xii.</note> ſayeth manefeſtlye, and S. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe S. Paules ſcoler, of the which S. Auſten writeth thus. <note place="margin">Lib. x. cae. xxii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in cene ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ram. Lib. iii. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. xiii. de lib arb. Lib. iiii. cap. 4. de bapti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra dona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Conſuetudo matris eccleſiae in baptizandis paruulis nequa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſper nenda eſt ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ullo modo ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flua deputanda, nec omnino cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denda, niſi apoſtolica eſset tradi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio.</hi> The accuſtomaunce of oure mother the Churche in bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge of children is in no wyſe to be diſpiſed, nor to be recke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſuperfluous by anye mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, nor vtterlye to be beleued, if it had not ben a traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:26296:41"/> Apoſtles. What ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our new tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and the makers of the articles afore mentioned, ſaye to theſe authorities for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe of their doctrine, that men are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to credite and beleue nothing, but that onlye, whiche the ſcripture ſetteth furthe? Woulde they, that men ſhoulde beleue them afore theſe auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, godly, &amp; great learned fathers? But of this mattier I haue written moore at large in my booke of traditions, &amp; therefore I now make an end of this cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piter, wiſſhinge grace and the knowledge of the trueth vnto all that erre in Chriſtes religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they may come at the le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ioyes of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thorough Chriſte oure ſauiours glorious paſſion, to whome with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:26296:41"/> and the holie ghoſte be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and prayſe for euer Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>The fourthe chapiter.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>That the ſoules of men departed do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not ſlea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, but either they goe to heauen for their good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> workes or els to Hell for their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uell before do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes daye.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Outhinge this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I wyll be verye ſhorte, becauſe I thinke that fewe of oure countree men are infected with this opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Chriſte ſaied to the theife hanginge with him vpon the croſſe. <hi>Hod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e mecum e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris in paradiſo.</hi> This daye thou <note place="margin">Luk. xxiii.</note> ſhalte be with me in paradiſe, that is to ſaye (as ſaint Auſten
<pb facs="tcp:26296:42"/> expoundeth it verye truelye.) this daye of my death thy ſoule being departed out of thy body, ſhall ſee the de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te, and god head clearly. Alſo ſainte Paule ſaied <note place="margin">Phil. i.</note> 
               <hi>Cupio diſolui &amp; eſse cum Chriſto.</hi> I deſire to die and to be with Chriſte, whiche is as muche as if he had ſayed, when I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte out of this worlde, I ſhall be ſtreighte waye with Chriſt, as he himſelfe declareth to the Corinthians, ſayinge thus. <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. v.</note> 
               <hi>Scimus quod ſi terreſtris do mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> noſtra &amp;c.</hi> We know that if our earthlye houſe of this dwelling be brooken, we haue a houſe of God in heauen not made with mans hande. Agayn he ſayeth. <hi>Audemus &amp; bonam uoluntatem</hi> 
               <note place="margin">ii. Cor. v.</note> 
               <hi>habemus, magis peregrinari à cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore, &amp; praeſentes eſse ad domin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:26296:42"/> We are bolde, and we haue a good wil, rather to be ſtrangers from the bodye, and to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with our lorde. Whiche is as muche as if he had ſayed, when I ſhall goo oute of thys worlde, than I haue a houſe in heauen, &amp; ſhalbe preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with our lord God. Whiche ſaint Hierom <note place="margin">Hier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, To. i. epiſt. ad Marcellam de obitu Leae.</note> affirmeth ſaying thus. <hi>Nunc illa pro breui labore, aeterna fruitur be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atitudine, excipitur a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> choris.</hi> Now ſhe hath the pleaſure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euerlaſtinge bliſſe, ſhe is recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with the compaignie of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. Sainte Auſten writtinge <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. in pſal, 10.</hi> Phil. i.</note> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this Paules ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. <hi>Cupio d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſsolui &amp;c.</hi> ſaieth. <hi>Viuit Paulus nunc cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſto<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſicut illi prophetae omnes viuunt cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſto.</hi> Sainte Paule liueth nowe with Chriſt, as all thoſe Prophetes doeth.
<pb facs="tcp:26296:43"/> Agayne Sainte Auſten ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge of the gate or porte of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, whiche Chriſte opened the daye of his death, writeth thus. <hi>Per ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e ingreſſus eſt Petrus, per hanc ingreſsus eſt Paulus, per hanc omnes ſancti Martyres intra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> Thorow this port S. Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter entred into heauen, through this gate ſ. Paule we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, through thys gate al the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie Martyrs entred into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Saint Baſill beleued the ſame, <note place="margin">Baſil. epiſt. 67.</note> when he ſaied thus. <hi>Mortuus eſt uir, qui columna erat, &amp; ſtabilime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tum eccleſiae, imo magis ad beata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> uitam ſublarus à nobis, abſceſsit.</hi> The man is deade, whiche was the piller, and the eſtabliſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the churche: Naye rather hee taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, is goone into hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen. Abdias, which was of the <note place="margin">Abdi. lib. i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>poſtilic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> lxxii. diſciples which Chriſt ſent
<pb facs="tcp:26296:43"/> in to the worlde afore him to preache, ſaieth that Saint Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſaied, when he ſhoulde be cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cified: <hi>Quare ſcito<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e me ad hoc ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum feſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are, ut carne exutus; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino aſſiſtam.</hi> Wherfore knowe ye that I make haſte vnto this ſame thinge, that I beinge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clothed of the fleaſhe, maye be preſent with our lorde.</p>
            <p>Again he witneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eth that S. <note place="margin">Lib. v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt. ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Iohn euangeliſt ſayd vnto one Andronicus, weping muche for the death of Druſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ana. <hi>Ita ne fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueris quaſi ignores, quo illa conceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerit? Neſcis illam conu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſationem eſſe meliorem, quae in coelo eſt ad quam ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cta &amp; fidelis, Druſiana tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſiuit, expectans ſpem reſurrectio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nis ex mortuis?</hi> Doeſt thou ſo weape for her as thoughe thou kneweſt not, whether ſhee is
<pb facs="tcp:26296:44"/> goone? Doeſt thou not knowe that that conuerſation is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whiche is in heauen, vnto the whiche the holye and faieth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Druſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is paſſed out of this life, looking for the riſinge vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine from death vnto lyfe? Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumenius a Greake writter, ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding theſe wordes of ſ. Ste<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen: <note place="margin">Actes. vii.</note> receaue O lorde Ieſu, my ſpirite, ſayeth. <hi>Hinc oſtendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur iuſtorum animas á cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poribus liberatas ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in infernum deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dere, ſed tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ mitti in manus Dei viuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:26296:44"/>
            <head>The fifte chapiter.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>That it is lawfull and good to put fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce, eſperaunce, or truſt in our good workes, nexte after God, as in his gif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, whiche thinge Luther, Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter Martyr, &amp; ſemblable others deui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Alſo that we maye lyue god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye for the heauenlye rewarde.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THe Prophet did putte truſt in his good works, when he ſayed. <hi>Memento</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal cxxxi.</note> 
               <hi>do mine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Dauid, &amp; omnis manſue tudinis eius.</hi> Remembre Dauid, O lorde, and all hys mekenes. Euen ſo did the good kinge Eze <note place="margin">iiii. Reg. xx.</note> chias ſayinge. <hi>Memento, domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, quo modo ambulauerim, coram <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e in veritate &amp; in corde perfecto &amp;c.</hi> Remembre, o Lorde, howe I haue walked, that is to ſaye,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:45"/> howe I haue liued before thee with a perfite faieth, and haue d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne thoſe thinges, whiche plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth <note place="margin">Phil. iii.</note> thee. Sainte Paule con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth this doctrine, when he ſaith: <hi>Noſtra conuerſatio eſt in coe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lis, vnde &amp; expectamus dominum noſtrum Ieſum Chriſtum &amp; ce.</hi> Our liuynge is heauenlye, and therfore we looke for oure lorde Ieſu Chriſte, whiche wyll re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme oure vile bodyes, and make them lyke vnto his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bodie. Chriſte ſayed. <hi>Sunt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Matth. xix.</note> 
               <hi>eunuchi &amp;c.</hi> Ther be ſome men, whiche haue choſen a continent lyfe for the kyngdome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as their ſtipende, and rewarde. Mooreouer, ſaied not the holye Prophete Dauid. <hi>Inclinaui cor</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. L. xix</note> 
               <hi>meum &amp;c.</hi> I haue bowed mye heart to kepe thy righteous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inaundementes
<pb facs="tcp:26296:45"/> for a rewarde. Commendeth not ſainte Paule the Coloſſians, becauſe they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed <note place="margin">Loloſſ. i. Hebr. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. xii<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> char<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ee, and gaue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines, <hi>propter ſpem repoſitam eis in coelis,</hi> for a rewarde layed vp in heauen, whiche they ſo doing hooped to haue? Saieth he not that Moyſes preferringe the <note place="margin">He. xi. &amp; xii.</note> reproches, which he ſuffered for Chriſtes ſake before the riches of Aegypte, looked vpon the rewarde to come<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Saith he not alſo, that Chriſt, when he ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, looked vpon the ioyes, whiche he ſhoulde haue by hys paſſion Now heare what ſome <note place="margin">The doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ences.</note> of the olde doctours ſaye in this matter, and firſt ſaint Auſtens min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, whiche ſayeth. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pro re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsione</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tom. ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. lx, de tempore.</note> 
               <hi>peccatorum, &amp; amore vite ae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nae, eleemoſy nà dederis,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:46"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>otum dextera facit.</hi> If thou doe geue an almes for to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne remiſſion of thy ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and for the loue of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng lyfe, thy ryght hande doth altogether, that is to ſaye, it is well doone.</p>
            <p>Saint Baſyl ſaieth. <hi>Iuſtus eſt is, qui nos ad tolerandos agones,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Baſil. epiſt. lx. Lege Baſ. de ve ra virginitate et ad interroga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tionem, 135.</note> 
               <hi>praemijs inuitat.</hi> God is righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, which ſterreth vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> rewar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des to ſuffer fightes. Howe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tymes did Chriſt moue the people to lyue godlye by promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to them euerlaſting lyfe? Saith he not amongeſt the reſt, <hi>Hoc fac, &amp; viues?</hi> Do y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> this, that <note place="margin">Luke. x.</note> is to ſay, helpe thy neadie neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour with almes geuinge, and thou ſhalt liue euer? Why then maye not I leafullie lyue well, vpon hope of that euerlaſtinge
<pb facs="tcp:26296:46"/> lyfe whiche he promiſeth to vs that doe well, and continue in doinge well vnto our liues end, as Paule dyd? Saint Paule, ſaieth. <hi>Non ſunt condigne paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes &amp;c.</hi> The afflictions, or tribu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lations <note place="margin">Rom. ix.</note> of this lyfe, are not wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thye the glorie to come. Whiche he wrot to prouoke vs, to ſuffre aduerſitees patientlie, hopyng to obtain thereby that reward. This is manifeſtlye taught by the ſcripture, ſayinge: <hi>Fiducia</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tob. iiii<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>magna erit omnibus, coram Deo ſummo, ele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>moſyna, facienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus eam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. Chriſoſtome expreſſeth the ſame playnelye writynge <note place="margin">Chriſoſt. h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u Math.</note> thus. <hi>Vnuſquiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> noſtrum in nul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>la re alia, ſpem ſuam, niſi poſt dei miſecordiam, in morum honeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te conſtituat.</hi> Let euerye one of
<pb facs="tcp:26296:47"/> vs put his affiaunce and truſte in no other thynge, nexte after Gods mercie, but in the hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of maners. Agayne he ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Homi. lxvi. in. Ioannem.</hi> Math. xx.</note> expoundinge theſe Chriſtes wordes <hi>Non eſt meum dare vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis &amp; ce. Dominus illo compelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, in gratia Dei primum, deinde in Iaboribus proprijs, omnem ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutem &amp; ſpem gloriae reponere.</hi> Our Lorde moued vs thither, to put firſt all our ſaluation, &amp; all our hope and eſperaunce of the glorie to come, in Gods grace, and then afterwarde in our owne labours. Thirdelye <note place="margin">To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ii. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tione<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4. delazaro.</note> he writeth after this ſorte. <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gens bonum in tuis ipſius bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factis collocare ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> It is a very good thynge to putte truſte in thyne owne good dedes. <hi>Vt ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res quód eleemoſina eſt benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:47"/> opuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non ſimpliciter i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>norum amicitijs ſed in amieitijs per ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mona p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtis, Chriſtus iuſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> te co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidere, dicens. Facite v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micos et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded thee to truſt in amities gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> throw <note place="margin">Luc. xvi.</note> almes, ſayinge. Make you fren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des by the mam man of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. &amp;c. To make an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de of this Chapter, dyd not S. Paule <note place="margin">ii. Tim. iiii.</note> bothe truſte in hys good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and alſo loke to haue a re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde in heauen for them, and not onely for has faith, when he ſayed? <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> certamen. &amp;c.</hi> I haue foughten a good batte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, I haue kepte my faythe, and haue ended my courſe of pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chynge and of good lyuynge, there nowe reſteth a crowne of ryghteouſnes, whiche God a ryghteous iudge ſhall render
<pb facs="tcp:26296:48"/> to me at that daye, and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye vnto me, but vnto them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, whiche doe loue hys com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynge vnto that iudgement. Wherfore I molte humblie and heartelye beſeche God of hys great mercie geue them grace, that are agaynſt thys Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like doctrine, to retourne vnto the veritie agayne, and leade their liues godlye in obſeruyng of Gods holy commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, that they maye iuſtlye put their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aunce and truſt in their owne good workes, as Gods <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> giftes, and loke ſtedfaſtlye to haue and inioye the glorye of heauen thereby, throughe the merites of Chriſt our ſauiours bleſſed Paſſion, to whom with the father &amp; the holy ghoſt be all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rayſe, &amp; honour for euer. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:26296:48"/>
            <head>The ſixte chapiter.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>That Baptiſme is not onlye a ſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and a marke of oure iuſtification and pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> onlie a ſeale and confir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mation of the ſame, as Peter Martyr <note place="margin">T. Lr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> Ryd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ye. Latechiſme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o. 35. 36. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. xxvi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. xxi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and the authours of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and articles <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> kynge Edward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and teach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>THys erroure, good chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian reader, is ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtlye againſte Goddes worde, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s nothing can be more. Therfore if me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue any grace, and regarde to Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rueth, hys honoure, and their owne ſoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s health, or ſaluation, they wyll, that yet are not inferte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with theſe newe opinions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of them, and abhorre the
<pb facs="tcp:26296:49"/> teachers of them, and they that are poyſoned with any ſuch doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne, wyll for ſake it, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace againe the verie true doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne of the cathelyke churche, when they ſhall ſee that there guides teachers, and preachers do ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> erre againſt the worde of GOD, as they do in thys pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> matter of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: but to entrepruiſe &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne this treatiſe, ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d not S. Iohan Baptiſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that Chriſte ſhoulde baptiſe the people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the holy ghoſt? What is that, if it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <note place="margin">Math. ii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> not Chriſte, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>aye God, to geue hys: holy eſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> thorowe grace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; forgeuenes of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>nes, to the perſonage that is bapt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in baptiſme? Agayne was Peter Martyr, and the makers of the articles annexed to the
<pb facs="tcp:26296:49"/> aboue re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſed cathechiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ither ſo ignoraunt, that they knewe not, or ſo malitious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the trueth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they would not beleue this chriſtes, ſaying? <hi>Quiſquis crediderit, &amp; baptizatus fuerit ſalu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Who ſoeuer, ſhal <note place="margin">Mar. vl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> beleue &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e baptiſed, ſhal be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued? Is not this playne enough againſt this hereſie, and alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Peter Martyr, with all others the Lutherans, and Swinglians, whiche ſaye that <note place="margin">Fayth only iuſtifieth not man.</note> we are iuſtified, and ſaued by faieth onelye? For doeth not Chriſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyne here faieth, and baptiſme together for the pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſemente <note place="margin">Reade ye that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with Peter Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rs doctrine and repent in tyme.</note> of oure ſaluation? Seeſt thou not then, reader, that oure newe brethren were verie blinde to ſaye, that bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme is but a marke of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation
<pb facs="tcp:26296:50"/> and a ſealyng of it onlie. Wyll anye man be yet ſo madd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to followe their doctrine, or to beleue their teachinge, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted bokes? But heare Chriſt againe to their further reproch, &amp; coni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>utation, ſayinge. <hi>Niſi quis &amp;c.</hi> Excepte a man be borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine <note place="margin">Ioa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of water, and the holye ghoſt, he ſhall not entre into the kingdome of heauen. What is it, I beſeche the, Chriſtien reader, here to be borne agayn, of the water and the ſpirite, if it be not a man to be borne ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually thorowe grace, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuenes of his ſinnes the chyld of God, whiche was borne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turallye of his mother the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne <note place="margin">Pſalm. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> of Gods ire, or wrathe, as ſaint Paule witneſſeth playnlye? Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth not alſo Chriſte heare <note place="margin">Epheſ. ii. Note this.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:26296:50"/> that a manne entreth into the realme or kingdome of heauen thorow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his newe byrth in bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and that without it, he ſhall not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e can enter into it? Is this baptiſme to be but a <note place="margin">Faieth one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ueth vs not, as our newe brech<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th.</note> ſigne and a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmation of our ſaluation, or faieth onlye to iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie man? Is it any other thing a man to be iuſtified, than to be borne agayne throughe the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kinge of the holye ghooſt, which is geuen to vs in baptiſme? <note place="margin">Ti iii.</note> Seeſt thou not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ones again, reader theſe Goſpellers blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ignorance in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures? Moreouer, ſaith not S. Paule, that we are grafted into <note place="margin">Rom. vi.</note> Chriſtes myſticall bodye, the churche, throughe baptiſme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sayeth he not in an other place that the Corrinthians were
<pb facs="tcp:26296:51"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26296:51"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:26296:52"/> waſhed, made holy, and iuſtified <note place="margin">This is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Martyr which ſaith that a child is a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</note> in the name of our Lorde Ieſu Chriſt, and in the ſpirite of god, meanynge by that waſhinge of them, their baptiſme? See wee not then, that ſaint Paule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leued a man to be made righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or iuſtified throughe bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and not by fayeth onlye? Is this baptiſme then to be but <note place="margin">Faith onely i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtifieth vs not.</note> a marke of oure ſaluation, and iuſtification? O notable and ſtraunge blyndnes of theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceders, yea of theſe goers back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward from the trueth, and new preachers. Why wynked they at thys ſayinge of ſaint Paule, <note place="margin">Gala. iii.</note> Ye all are the ſonnes of GOD, thorowe faieth, whiche is in Chriſte Ieſu? <hi>Quot quot nam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Chriſto baptizati eſtis, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum induiſtis.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:26296:52"/> For as manye of you as be bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſed in Chriſte, haue putte on Chriſt. What els ment ſayn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Paule here, by puttynge on of Chriſt in Baptiſme, but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauinge of hym by grace, that we made the children of God his father, not onely by faythe, (as this letter declareth) but alſo by baptiſme, ſhoulde be clo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thed with him, and our ſynnes ſo remitted throughe his deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and ſpeciall grace, that they ſhould be therby as it were co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered and hidde from the ſyght of God, that he wyll not looke vpon them to puniſhe vs for them? Dyd theſe men neuer reade, and vnderſtande ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et Paule, affirmynge, that Chriſt cleanſeth vs through the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne <note place="margin">Ephe. v.</note> of water, and the worde
<pb facs="tcp:26296:53"/> of lyfe, to make vs glorious without ſpotte, and wrincle of ſynne? Wyll then anye learned wyſe man yet beleue this doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, <note place="margin">Faith onely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth vs not.</note> whiche is, that only fayth iuſtifieth man, and that baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me is but a ſygne, or a marke onelye of it? Adde to theſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges thys teſtimonie of S. Paule. <hi>Cum apparuerit benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitas &amp;c.</hi> After the bounteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and loue of oure ſauioure God, whiche he bare towarde man appeared, he of hys mercie ſaued vs, &amp; not of oure ryghte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous workes, throughe the foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne <note place="margin">Baptiſme is not only a mark of our iuſtifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ation but a cauſe of it.</note> of renewynge and rege<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neration, or bearyng vs againe of the holye ghoſt, whiche he powred into vs plenteouſlye, throughe Ieſus Chriſte oure ſauiour, that we beynge iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:26296:53"/> by hys grace, ſhuld be heires of eternall lyfe, thorowe eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce or hoope. Who may not ſee here moſte playnly, that S. Paule affirmeth a man to bee ſaued, renewed, borne agayne, and iuſtified by baptiſme, and the holye Ghoſte alſo to bee geuen to vs in it? Where was then theſe mens learnyng in the ſcriptures, when they ſo ignorauntlye taughte the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye, ſayinge: that baptiſme is but a token, marke, ſeale, and confirmation of our iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on <note place="margin">Fayth only iuſtifieth not man.</note> and ſaluation, and that only fayth doeth iuſtifie vs? Oure Lorde tourne theyr heartes to his trouth agayne, out of thys ſtraunge blyndnes, in whiche they are. Finallye touchyng the rehearſall of the Scriptures,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:54"/> ſaith not ſ. Peter that as N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es <note place="margin">i. Peter. iii.</note> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke or ſhyppe ſaued hym, and ſeuen other from drownynge in the floude<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> euen ſemblablye baptiſme ſaueth vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Wherefore retourne ye Swinglians and Lutherans to the Catholyke churche, and forſakynge youre errours and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> naughtye opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, embrace the trueth agayn, whiche the holye &amp; notable doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tours hath taught vs in theyr bookes, as it appeareth mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtlye by ſome of theyr ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whiche I haue annexed to theſe ſcriptures, that thereby men maye playnelye ſee, that oure newe brethren are not membres of Chriſtes catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like churche, nor beleue as thoſe fathers dyd, whiche are nowe Sainctes in heauen.
<pb facs="tcp:26296:54"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of ſome of the auncient wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>des, and iudgementes, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ce and ſtrength of bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, againſt Peter Martyr &amp; al the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e. Swinglians &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>h do affirme that it is but onely a ſigne and a confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of our iuſtification, and no cauſe thereof.</p>
            <p>Saint Auſten writeth after thys manie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Vnuſquis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Serm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. xvi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> verbis apoſt.</note> 
               <hi>iuſtificatione conſtitutus, accepta ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>licet. remiſsione peccatorum per <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auacrum regenerationis, accepto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>piritu ſancto, proficiens de die in diem, uideat, ubi ſit.</hi> Let euer ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <note place="margin">We dooe r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuenes of oure ſinnes &amp; the holye ghoſt in and by baptiſme</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>han he is iuſtified, and remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his ſynues beyng recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> thorowe the fountaine of baptiſme, in which man is born agayne, and alſo when he hath the holye Ghooſt throughe the ſame baptiſme, take heede, loke
<pb facs="tcp:26296:55"/> or conſidre in what eſtate he is profitinge or goinge forwarde daylye in grace, and vertuous lyuinge. Thys is veraye plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye written, but heare hym a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne writing more playnlye in <note place="margin">To<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Pelag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anum.</note> thys matter. <hi>Iuſtificato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſecundum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſta tria confertur, prius lauacro regenerationis, quo remittuntur cuncta p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ata. Dein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de congreſsione cum uitijs, à quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> reatu ſoluti ſumus. Tertio dum no ſtra exauditur oratio, qua dicimus. Dimitte nobis debita noſtra &amp; ce.</hi> That is to ſaye, iuſtification is <note place="margin">Mat. vi.</note> geuen to vs in thys life by theſe <note place="margin">We are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by in thinges <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd not by faith only as our new ghooſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs do ſai falſlye.</note> three thynges<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Fyrſte throughe baptiſme, in the whiche we are borne agayne and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are forgeuen vs. Secondlye we are made righteous by figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge with our vices, from the
<pb facs="tcp:26296:55"/> gylte, or faulte of whiche, we be looſed. Thirdlye iuſtification is geuen to vs, when thys oure petition is gratiouſlye harde: Forgeue vs, O father, whiche arte in heauen, oure treſpaſſes committed againſte the, as wee do forgeue them, that treſpaſſe againſte vs. <hi>Aqua exhibet forin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ecus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Grace is ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen by bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</note> 
               <hi>ſacramentum gratiae, &amp; ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tus operatur intrinſecus benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m gratiae, ſoluens uinculum cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pae, reconcilians bonum naturae, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>generat hominem in vno chriſto, ex uno Adam generatum.</hi> The water exhibiteth outwardly the ſacrament of grace, and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ghoſte worketh inwardelye the benefite of grace, looſynge the bonde of ſynne, and recon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciling the goodnes of nature: it doeth regenerat a man in, or
<pb facs="tcp:26296:56"/> thorowe one Chriſte, begotten of one Adam. What can our bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren <note place="margin">Faith onlie tuſtifieth not man.</note> thren ſay to this, which defende that faieth onlye iuſtifeth man, and that baptiſme is but onelye a marke of our iuſtification, and a ſeale of it? Heare him agayne ſaying. <hi>Illo ſacroſancto lauacro in choatur renouatio noui hominis.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. i. demo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ae. orum, ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> xxxv.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The renewinge of the newe man is begon throughe the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye lauatorie, or fountaygne of baptiſme. <hi>Dicimus baptiſma dare</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Then oure new brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are not ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tholyke me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but playne ſciſmatikes.</note> 
               <hi>in dulgentiam omnium peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, et auferre crimina, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> radere.</hi> We catholyke men doe affime, that baptiſme geueth to vs re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſion of all oure ſynnes, and taketh cleane away our ſinnes, &amp; not as it were to ſhaue them, that the rootes of them remayn ſtyll. <hi>Baptiſma abluit peccata om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:56"/> prorſus omnia, dictorum facto</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. i. ca. xiii. contra duas epiſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alogi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rum.</note> 
               <hi>rum ac cogitatoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſiue originalia, ſiue addita &amp;c.</hi> Baptiſme waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth awaye all ſynnes, vtterly al, of wordes, deedes, &amp; though<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, whether thei be originales, or added, that is to ſaye, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall <note place="margin">Baptiſme putteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye oure ſynnes, and not faieth onlye.</note> ſynnes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted by mans owne acte and free wyll. Howe ſhamfully then are Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyr and all the newe brethren deceaued, whiche ſaye that bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme is no cauſe of our iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, but faieth onelye, and that baptiſme is but a marke of it, and a confirmation, and yet ſay that they do ſetfurth the faieth, and religion of the fathers and of the olde catholyke churche? He that luſteth to reade more of thys matter in ſainte Auſtens workes, let hym go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the pla <note place="margin">Lib. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ad catech. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cap. x.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:26296:57"/> ces alleaged here, and noted in the margent of thys treatiſe, &amp; <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. ix. tract. v. in primam. Io. epiſt. To. x. ſer. 128. de tempore tract. 80. in Io.</note> he ſhall be fullye ſatisfied of his beleife herin, notwithſtanding, that theſe ſentences alreadye recited, maye ſatisfie euerye good man. Heare howe what was ſainte Hieroins beleife in thys mater, whiche ſayeth. <hi>Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gelij mihiplacet religio, vt baptize mini in fanguine meo, per lauacru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hieroni. in ca. i. Eſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>regeneration is, quod ſolum poteſt dimittere peccata, iuxta illud. Niſi quis renatus fuerit &amp;c.</hi> The reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the Euangelie (ſayeth Hiero<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Chriſtes perſone) plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth me, that ye be baptiſed in my bloude, through the lauato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of regeneration, whiche on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye can remitte ſynnes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to thys ſaying of Chriſte. Excepte a man be borne againe
<pb facs="tcp:26296:57"/> of water and the holie ghoſt, he <note place="margin">Ioan. iii. Note this reader.</note> ſhall not entre into the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen. What can Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter Martyr and his followers ſaie to thys playne ſentence?</p>
            <p>Wyll they arrogantlye denye theſe doctours ſayinges and thoſe that follow here, deſiring that men ſhoulde rather credit and beleue them, than thoſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye aunciente great clerkes, as Latymer did of late in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations kepte at Oxforde, <note place="margin">Latimer.</note> when he coulde not aunſwere to them? Saint Hierom ſayeth, onlye: baptiſme is the meane to obtaine forgeues of our ſinnes, and Peter Martyr ſaieth, faith onelye is, and that baptiſme is onely a ſigne of it, and no cauſe. He ſaieth againe. <hi>Chriſtus bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſma</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hieroni. in c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ad Gala<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>in Iordanis fluento, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dcir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26296:58"/> quaſi poeni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ens, quu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſet à pecca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis liber, accepit, ut coeteros edoce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret mundandos eſſe per baptiſma, &amp; in filios noua ſpiritus adoptione regenerari:</hi> Chriſte receaued bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme in the ryuer of Iordane therfore, as a penitent perſone, althoughe he was free frome ſynne, that he myghte thereby, <note place="margin">Note this good reader well.</note> teache other menne, that they muſt be made cleane frome the filthynes of ſynne throughe bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme, and be borne agayne the ſonnes of God by the adoption of the holye ghoſt. Origen was of the ſelfe ſame beleife in thys <note place="margin">Origenes hom. v. in loſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> mattier, whiche wrote this. <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r baptiſma regenerationis expurga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae ſunt animae noſtrae.</hi> Our ſoules are cleanſed throughe baptiſme of a newe byrthe. Agayne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <note place="margin">Homi. ii. in Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>cum. Cy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>illus.</note> and ſainte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yrill followynge
<pb facs="tcp:26296:58"/> hym, doe ſaye thus. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>di nunc, quantae ſunt in euangelijs peccato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum remiſsiones. Eſt prima, qua baptizamur in remiſsionem pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorum.</hi> Heare now how many wayes there are in the euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les to obtayn remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes. The fyrſt is, by whiche we are baptiſed to pourchace forgeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſynne. <hi>Deus abolet ſine du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bio uitium primae natiuitat is per regenerationem.</hi> God withoute doubtaunce putteth awaye the ſyn of oure fyrſt byrth through oure newe byrth in baptiſme. Chryſoſtome eſtabliſheth thys doctrine ſaying. <hi>Futurum erat</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Chry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oſt. hom. xxxv. in eua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Ioann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> 
               <hi>baptiſma plenum maximae poteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis, &amp; gratiae purgaturum pecca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta pro mortuo viuum effecturum.</hi> Baptiſme was to come, full of greateſt puiſſaunce, or power,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:59"/> and of grace, whiche ſhoulde pourge or cleanſe mens ſoules from their ſynnes, and make a man alyue ſpirituallye, whiche was deade afore thorowe ſinne. Agayne he ſaieth <hi>Aufert quidem</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Serm. iiii. in ca. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ad Epheſios</note> 
               <hi>deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in praeſenti uita iniquitates, et per lauacrum regenerationis, et per poenitentiam.</hi> God taketh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye mennes ſynnes in thys <note place="margin">Note this againſte the ſolif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dians.</note> preſent lyfe, bothe throughe bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme, and alſo throughe pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce. <hi>Iuſtificauit deus per laua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cri</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Serm. xv. in ca. ix. ad Rom.</note> 
               <hi>regenerationem.</hi> God hathe iuſtified man throughe the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatorie of regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He ſaith alſo that oure circumciſion (bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme) bringeth to vs goodes without numbre, and that it fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <note place="margin">Hom xxxix. in Geneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>os ca. 17.</note> vs full of the holye ghoſtes grace, and that it hathe no time appointed for the adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:26296:59"/> of it: Tertullia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beleued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, ſayinge. <hi>Caro abluitur, ut anima emaculetur.</hi> The body of man is <note place="margin">Tertul. de re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſur. car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> is waſhed, that his ſoule may be made cleane fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſpottes of ſinne. Saint Cyprian, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth to theſe fathers, when he ſayth thus: <hi>Gratia de baptiſmi</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>piſt. iii</note> 
               <hi>ſanctification<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> percipitur.</hi> Grace is receaued throughe the halo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winge of mannes ſoule in bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. <hi>per baptiſma ſpiritus ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus percipitur.</hi> The holy ghoſt is receaued by or throughe bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. <hi>Oportet mundari, &amp; ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficari</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. ii. epiſt. iii. &amp; lib. i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pi. xi<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>aquam prius à ſacerdote, vt poſsit baptiſmo ſuo peccatà homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, qui baptizatur, abluere.</hi> The water muſt be firſt made cleane and holye of the prieite, that it <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alowinge of the fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te <hi>Lib. in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. cp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. vii.</hi>
               </note> maye throughe the waſhinge of it, waſhe awai the mans ſinnes
<pb facs="tcp:26296:60"/> whiche is baptiſed. To be ſhort he ſayeth that all the Deuels myght and power is taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him in baptiſme, and the grace of the holye Ghooſte is equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye geuen to vs in it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sciat diaboli nequitiam pertina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Lib. 4. epiſt. 7.</note> 
               <hi>uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ad aquam ſalutarem va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere, in baptiſmo autem omnes vires nequitiae amittere.</hi> Lette<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> man knowe that the dyuels ſtubborne euelnes or malice is ſtronge continually vnto the water of ſaluation, but in bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme he loſeth all his power to do euyll. <hi>Quos parentalis labes infecerat, ſic lauat baptiſmus, vt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Marke this ſayinge.</note> 
               <hi>nec actualis, nec originalis macula aliqua poſt ablutionem il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigia derelinquat.</hi> Baptiſme doeth ſo cleane waſhe theym, whiche Adams ſynne had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected
<pb facs="tcp:26296:60"/> or defiled, that no ſpotte nother of originall ſynne nor of <note place="margin">The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſence re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maininge in the chylde baptiſed is no ſynne.</note> actuall after that waſhynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of fylth, leaueth any print, token, or ſigne. Is this baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me to be but onelye a marke of our iuſtification, or a ſealynge of it? Is this faythe onelye to iuſtifie vs, and baptiſme to bee no cauſe of our ryghtuouſnes, and iuſtification? O how blinde are theſe brethren, whiche doe teache that, &amp; ſemblable other wicked doctrine. Our lord geue them grace to recule and retier to the trouth from their here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies. Heare S. Baſyll, whiche <note place="margin">Baſ. de exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ue ad bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſmum.</note> was almoſte twelue hundred yeres ſence. <hi>Baptiſma captiuoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt redemptio, debitoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> remiſsio, mors peccatorum, animae rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neratio, amictus ſplendens, chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter
<pb facs="tcp:26296:61"/> indeprehenſibilis, coeli ite<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, regni coeleſtis conciliatio, adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis gratia.</hi> Baptiſme is a raun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom <note place="margin">Many bene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fites obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſme. Marke. Ioa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. iii.</note> of priſoners, a forgeuenes of debtes, the death of ſynnes, a regeneration of the ſoule, a bright apparell, a figure that can not be perfitlye perceaued, the iourneye of or to heauen, the purchaſyng of the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye kyngdome, the grace of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>option, or choſynge of a man to be the chylde of God, and hys heyre. He hathe alſo theſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences amongeſt manye moe. <hi>Tempus aliud alij opportunum negocio quaerunt, ad baptiſmi ve<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ro ſalutem, tempus quodlibet acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>modum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> baptiſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ſit, ſiue dies, ſiue nox, ſiue hora, ſiue quodcun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> temporis momentum.</hi> Men doe ſeke dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers tymes conuenient for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers
<pb facs="tcp:26296:61"/> buſyneſſes, but euery ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon maye or ſhoulde be meete <note place="margin">Our newe brethren ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted a time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eyue bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme.</note> to receaue ſaluation throughe baptiſme, whether it be daye, or nyght, houre, or anye other ſhorte tyme. Agayne he ſayeth, <hi>Peccatum gratiam nobis per bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmi regenerationem datam abo</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Hom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in pſal. xxviii.</note> 
               <hi>let.</hi> Synne putteth awaye grace, geuen to vs throughe baptiſme, in whyche we are borne agayne. <hi>Seruamur, autem, quo modo? Nimiru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regenerati per</hi> 
               <note place="margin">De exhorta, ad baptiſma.</note> 
               <hi>gratiam, quae confertur in baptiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mo.</hi> We are ſaued, but howe? Vndoubtedly throughe Gods grace, whiche is geuen to vs in baptiſme. Was not then Peter <note place="margin">Fayth! only ſaueth not, howe be it our new bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren ſaye that it doth.</note> Martyr very ignoraunt, when he affirmed and defended that our ſaluation conſiſted onelye in God, and that baptiſme is
<pb facs="tcp:26296:62"/> but a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>igne, and an eſtabliſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our ſaluation? S. Martiall <note place="margin">Epiſt. i. cap. 5.</note> S. Peters diſciple <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>areth. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiuiſcit anima per baptiſma. Iam ſanctificat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; mundati eſtis aqua regenerationis.</hi> The ſoule of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> waxeth alyue throughe bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: You are now made holye and cleane from the fylthynes of ſynne, by or with the water of baptiſme, in whiche ye are borne agayne. S. Gregore, Hieroms mayſter, affirmeth the ſame thynge ſayinge <hi>Laua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crum eorum qui peccauerunt, non</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ratione in ſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>auacrum.</note> 
               <hi>qui peccant, remiſs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onem conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net.</hi> His ſcoler Eucherius was of the ſame belief, which wrote thus. <hi>Salutis vnda nos à primi parentis culpa abſoluit.</hi> The wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> libres regu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> louſeth vs from the ſynne of our firſt father A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:62"/> whiche is originall ſynne. Erred not then Peter Martyr when he taughte at Oxforde, that a Chriſtian mans chylde obtayneth remiſſion of original ſynne before he bee baptized, and that he ſhall be ſaued yf he be not baptized at all? Whyche doctrine ryſeth of that other, that fayth onelye doeth iuſtifie vs. Arator an olde writer hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <note place="margin">Lib i. cap. ii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in act, apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> with thys catholyke doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine ſayinge:</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Siſol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere cur a eſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Faecundi crementa mali, faelicibus vndi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Extinctu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reparate genus, ſpes vn a remitti,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Debita ſupplicii, poſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rimina Velle renaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>S. Alch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mus Archebyſhop of <note place="margin">An. domi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Lib. 5. cap. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> Geneſ.</note> Vienna an ancient writer hath thus.
<pb facs="tcp:26296:63"/> 
               <hi>Quu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> purgata ſacris debitur culpa fluentis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> noua parientis lympha lauacri, Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> poſt veteres, quos aedidit Eua, reatus.</hi> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>audius Varius Victor, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che was aboute xi. hundred yeres paſſed, hathe ſette furthe <note place="margin">Lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gen.</note> this godlye doctrine, when he wrote thus.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Poſse perire homines docuit, mergentibus vndis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oftendit flammis, ac vndis poſse renaſci.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>S. Pauline, that was in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtens tyme and wrote to hym, <note place="margin">Natali. x. f. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. cis</note> is in thys matter agaynſt Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Martyr, and ſuche others, writynge thus.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sic pariter templum nouat hoſtis, gratiae fontem,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fons<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> nouus renouans homines. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Euſebius confirmeth this ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike <note place="margin">L. b. 9. capita. Euangelica demonſtra.</note> doctrine, when he ſaith. <hi>Non amplius per legitima ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficia
<pb facs="tcp:26296:63"/> Moſaicae legis, remiſsio illis peccatorum conciliatur, ſed pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lauacri purgatione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quod in colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta ex gentibus eccleſia tradeba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> Remiſſion of ſynne is no longer purchaſed of theym throughe the lawfull ſacrifices of Moyſes lawe, but throughe the cleanſynge of the fountaine of baptiſme, which was geuen in the churche aſſembled of the Gentils.</p>
            <p>Thys is playnelye ſayde, and as playne is thys ſentence, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced and publiſhed in the fyrſte counſayle holden at the citie of Nicea, almoſte twelue hundred yeres ſence. <hi>Confiteo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>m baptiſma in remiſsionem peccatorum.</hi> That is to ſaye. <note place="margin">Note thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> reader.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I do confeſſe, or acknowledge, that there is one baptiſme, or
<pb facs="tcp:26296:64"/> that a man muſt be ones bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to obtain remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes. Thys is the Crede and beleife <note place="margin">Epheſ. iiii. Peter mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr and the new brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beleue not a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the holye catholyke church doth.</note> of al chriſtian nations, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. I maye well conclude a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Peter Martyr, and the makers of the afore recited ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme, and the articles adioy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to the ſame, that they are not membres of Chriſtes holye churche, becauſe they ſaye that baptiſme is but a ſigne, token, marke, and confirmation of our iuſtification, and of the remiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſynnes, but that they are forgeuen vs by fayeth onlye before we be baptiſed, yea wee beinge chyldren latelye borne &amp; hauing no fayth of our owne. Saint Ambroſe agreeth herein with the other fathers ſpeaking <note place="margin">Ambroſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in i. Cor.</note> of our waſſhing in baptiſme, of
<pb facs="tcp:26296:64"/> our being halowed in baptiſme, <note place="margin">Faieth onlye doeth not iuſtifie man, but baptiſme al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo.</note> &amp; of oure iuſtification obtained therin, as Paule witneſſeth in that place. <hi>Haec omnia beneficia puritatis, in baptiſmate conſecuti noſcuntur, quod eſt fundamentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uangelicae ueritatis. Illic enim om<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nibus pec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> depoſitis, abluitur credens, &amp; iuſtificatur in nomine domini, &amp; ſpiritu dei noſtri, filius deo adoptatur.</hi> The people are knowen to haue gotten all theſe benefites of purenes in baptiſm <note place="margin">Note this, reader, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentlye.</note> whiche baptiſme is the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of the trueth of the euangell. For in baptiſme he that bele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth is waſſhed cleane from his ſynnes, and is iuſtified in the name of our lorde, and thorowe the ſpirite of God is choſen the ſonne of God, al hys ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put away from hym. Seeſt
<pb facs="tcp:26296:65"/> thou not here playnelye, reader, <note place="margin">The vertue and ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, of baptiſme.</note> that ſaint Ambroſe expo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nding ſaint Pauls wordes, declareth that he mente, that we are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fied in baptiſme, and do receaue therby the holye ghoſt, obtayne remiſſion of al our ſinnes, &amp; are made the ſonnes or chyldren of God by adoption, whiche alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether Peter Martyr denieth vngodlye? Ought he then to be credited &amp; beleued in his other opinions, whiche doeth ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauntlye erre in this mattier a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte the holye ſcriptures, the general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelles, the doctours, the auncient cuſtome, and the beleife of the catholike churche? Heare the holye man Leo the fyrſt Pope of that name, which <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eo ſermone primo de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ate Chriſti.</note> was aboue M. C. yeres ſynce, and ſaieth. <hi>Per baptiſmatis ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:65"/> ſpiritus ſancti factus es templum.</hi> Thou arte made the temple of the holye Ghooſte throughe the ſacrament of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme. Maximus an auncient great learned man was of the <note place="margin">Homi. de ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolo apoſt.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ame beleife, when he wrote thus. <hi>Sancta eſt eccleſia, quae bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmi ſacramento, peccatorum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagione deterſa, terrarum incolas tranſmittit ad coelum.</hi> The church is holye, whiche ſendeth the dwellers of the earthes vnto heauen, throughe the ſacrament of baptiſme, the infectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes being therby wyppen or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken awaye. This is manifeſtlye ſpoken of theſe holye doctours. I paſſe ouer all the reſte of the olde doctours ſentences, boeth becauſe theſe are ſufficiente to perſuade euery man, that is not
<pb facs="tcp:26296:66"/> obſtinatlye geuen to abyde in his errour, and alſo for that, that I woulde not be ouer te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious to the reader. Our lorde of hys infinite goodnes, &amp; moſte tendre mercye graunte them grace to amende, and to forſake thys wicked errour, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers their abominable opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to retourne agayne vnto Chriſtes catholyke church leauinge their ſchiſme, to the honoure of God and the ſaluation of their own ſoules. which Chriſte bought moſt dear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e with the ſhed dynge of hys preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bloude<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:26296:66"/>
            <div type="preface">
               <head>The preface to the vii. chapiter.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That vowes ought to be kept both of men, &amp; alſo of wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Peter Martyr, &amp; the whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ment of the new brethren, and eſpecially againſt the maried mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>kes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hanons, Fre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs, and N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nnes.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THen I perceaued, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that manye, whiche hadde made vowes to God of perpetual chaſtitee, we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> maried thorowe the enticement and alluringe of the deuell, the fleaſhe, and the world, and that their doinges was againſte the worde of God, to their owne vttermoſt da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation, I thought it good, and nedefull breifelie to treate of thys mattier, that they, whiche are offendours
<pb facs="tcp:26296:67"/> therin, mighte playnlye ſee, in what perell they ſtande, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide it in tyme. And for as muche as many men, eſpeciallye ſuche as are detained, and e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peched with many great a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, delite in thinges brefelye ſetfurthe, I wyll vſe in thys treatiſe a breuitee of wordes, and alleage but a certain of the olde doctours ſentences writté in thys controuerſie. But I wil commence and begynne with the ſcriptures, and then addreſſe to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holye fathers mindes therof, that euery man may ſee therby, both that thys doctrine is not newe (as oure newe men ſaye) and alſo howe ab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mina<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blye M. Luther the frere, Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Bucer the frere, Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyr the chanon of ſaint Auſtens
<pb facs="tcp:26296:67"/> rule, Iohan Hoper the white mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke, Couerdale the frere, Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer the chanon, &amp; ſemblable o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>otaries, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ed, &amp; brought manye mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into their errours, and hereſies, God permittynge them ſo euidentlye and ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye to fall for the puniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their ſinnes, as he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered the Gentyles to runne headlynge, as it were, into vices mooſt deteſtable, and into a reproued minde (as ſaint Paule <note place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> witneſſeth) ſo to be auenged on them for their former offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes. But I wyl ſet vpon this entre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, and diſpatche it breifelye, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> right worthy doctour Thomas Marten, hathe writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <note place="margin">Doctour Martens boke agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> prieſtes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages.</note> therof both learnedly &amp; largely. Thou ſhalt good reader, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande that all ſuche places
<pb facs="tcp:26296:68"/> of the ſcripture, whiche doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of vs generallye the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmance and accompliſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our vowes godlye made vnto God, doeth ſhewe that menne muſt neades vpon pain of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge damnation, kepe, not onlye the vowe of chaſtitee, but alſo of pouertie, of obeiſaunce, and of al others. Wherefore let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be offended with me, that I am ſo playne in thys mattier againſt their breakinge of their vowes, for the trueth oughte to be pleaſaunte to euerye good man, whiche regardeth Gods glorie, and hys owne ſaluation. Saint Paule reproued the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lathian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <note place="margin">Gala. iiii.</note> verie ſharplye, becauſe they were offended with hym for teachinge them the trueth.</p>
               <p>If anye man be diſpleaſed
<pb facs="tcp:26296:68"/> with this my ſettynge furthe of Gods holye veritie, he ſhall geue to me a iuſte occaſion to ſaye vnto hym, as S. Paule ſayed vnto the Galathians. Who hathe bewitched and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſched <note place="margin">Gal. iii. iiii.</note> thee, that thou obeyeſt not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth? Our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, whiche is (as he ſayed) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. xiiii.</note> veritie, geue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, againſt whoſe faultes this traicte is written, grace to remembre that Chriſt ſayde. <hi>Si veritatem dico. &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If I tell you the trueth, why <note place="margin">Iohn. ix.</note> doe you not beleue me? He that <note place="margin">Note this,</note> is of God, doeth here the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of God, ye therefore do not heare Gods wordes, becauſe ye are not of God. What man is ſo ſtonye hearted, that theſe wordes can not moue hym?</p>
               <p>Doeth not theſe Chriſtes wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:26296:69"/> declare, that they are not Gods children, nor the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of ſaluation, whiche wyll not beleue &amp; folowe the trueth opened to them? I ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt them here, that vowed pouertie, &amp; renounced vtterly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proprietie of goodes, when the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> were profeſſed, and doe not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhe that theyr vowe, but are beneficed, yea haue diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s benefices, dignities, &amp; promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and doe gather together thereby much ryches. But this ſhoulde not offende anye man, for I teache them Gods word, and trueth. Which embraſed of them, and folowed, ſhall (as Chriſt ſayde to the Iewes) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer them from the peryll of <note place="margin">Iohn. ix.</note> damnation. Wyll not ſuche vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries call to their myndes
<pb facs="tcp:26296:69"/> this Chriſtes ſayinge? What doeth it profi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e a manne, yf he <note place="margin">Iohn, xvi</note> gayne all the worlde, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by loſe hys ſoule? What ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunge ſhall a man make for his ſoule? Were we not al borne naked, and ſhall beare nothyng oute of thys worlde wyth vs, as S. Paule ſayeth</p>
               <p>Wherfore let euerye man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue <note place="margin">i. Tim. vi.</note> (as Paule commaundeth vs) in his owne vocation, and <note place="margin">i. Cor. vii.</note> ſerue God therein godly, let no man looke backewarde with Lothes wife leſt he periſh. Let euerye man remembre, that Chriſte ſayed. No man putting <note place="margin">Luc. ix.</note> his hande to the plowe, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge behynde hym, is meete for the kingdome of heauen.</p>
               <p>S. Paule ſayeth agayne, that <note place="margin">ii. Tim. ii,</note> no man ſhalbe crowned, except
<pb facs="tcp:26296:70"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e fyghte lawfullye, that is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaye: no man ſhall obtayne the crowne of bliſſe, except he fight agaynſt the Deuell, the ficſhe, and the worlde, manlye and couragiouſlye, in his owne cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge, degree<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and eſtate, accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge to the lawes, and ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunces of hys vocation, and profeſſion. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>herfore to end this preface, I aduiſe, yea God doth aduiſe, euerye man and woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <note place="margin">Pſal. lxxv.</note> whiche hathe vowed chaſtitie, and pouertie to pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fourme that theyr godlye vowes to the ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uauncement, and encreaſe of Gods honoure, and to their owne ſaluation, that at the ende of theyr mortall lyues, Chriſte maye ſaye vnto theym, amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt the reſt: our good and faythfull ſeruanntes, enter ye <note place="margin">Math. xxv.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26296:70"/> into the ioyes of youre Lorde. Vnto whome be laude, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for euer, and euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter_proper">
               <head>The ſeuenth chapiter.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That al godly vowes, as the vowe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> continual chaſtic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y amydowe, the vow of wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful or volu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, and ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ables, ough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> by Gods lawe to be obſerued vnder, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ayne of euerlaſtinge damna<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I ſaw, good reader, that very manye of our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>treymen and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men nowe of late in the miſera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e alteration of Chriſtes holye religion, whiche was of late in thys Realme)
<pb facs="tcp:26296:71"/> were runne headlynge into a dampnable eſtate throughe breache of theyr vowes, I thought it nedefull, and my bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e to aduertiſe theym therof, that they ſeyng in what peryll and daunger they ſtande in, myght by Gods ſuccour and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yde auoyde it in tyme.</p>
               <p>Wherfore let them waygh di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently theſe places of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſcripture, whiche are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtlye agaynſt their doynges. <hi>Si quis viroium votum domino vouerit, aut ſe conſtrinxerit iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. xxx.</note> 
                  <hi>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n faciet irritu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verbum ſuum, ſed omne quod premiſit, implebit.</hi> If anye man ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake a vowe to our lord God, or ſhal bynde hym ſelfe with an othe, lette hym not breake hys
<pb facs="tcp:26296:71"/> worde, but he ſhall fulfyll all that he hathe promiſed. Can there be any thyng more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, <note place="margin">Note this ye votaries and beware of danuger.</note> ſpoken agaynſt them, that doe breake their vowes and promyſſes made to God of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie, and voluntarie pouertie? Seeſt thou not here reader, that religious perſonnes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che haue vowed pouertie, and haue willynglye forſaken the proprietie of worldlye goodes, doe breake that theyr vowe, <note place="margin">The vowe of pouertie.</note> and<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> promes, when they take benefices, prebendes, and ſuche other promotions, enrichynge them ſelues thereby, as muche as other doe, that neuer made anye ſuche vowe? Why reade they not this verſe of Dauid? <hi>Vouete, et reddite domino deo</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. lxx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>veſtro omnes qui in circuitu eius
<pb facs="tcp:26296:72"/> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffertis munera.</hi> Vowe and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your vowes to youre lorde God, ye all men that doe offer giftes vnto God in his circuite. Doeth not GOD require here the accompliſhement and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmaunce of all godlye vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes made to hym? Salomon ſetteth furth the ſame doctrine, <note place="margin">Eccle. v.</note> ſayinge. <hi>Si quid vouiſti Deo, ne moreris reddere, diſplicet enim <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſtulta et in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>idelis promi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>sio, ſed quod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>un<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> voueris redde, &amp; ce.</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thou haſte vowed anye thynge <note place="margin">A vow of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nectie ought to be kept, &amp; all others lawfullye made.</note> to God, tarye not to render it. For a folyſhe and an vnfayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full promyſſe diſpleaſeth hym, but what thynge ſo euer thou haſte, or ſhalt vowe, perfourme it. Who ſeeth not here euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye (excepte he be blinded with carnall affection) that the holy
<pb facs="tcp:26296:72"/> goſt forbiddeth here y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> breaking of all leafull vowes, and godlye promiſſes, both of chaſtitie, and volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tarie pouerte? What meane then our vowe breakers, when they can not abide him that tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth them their dueties to god for their ſaluation? Ought they to be angrie with him, that tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them the truth? Why reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre not they theſe Chriſtes wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des? <note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th. xvi. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. viii.</note> What ſhall it profitte a man, thoughe he ſhoulde winne all the whole worlde, if he looſe hys owne ſoule? But let them heare the ſcripture agayne, for a further, and a more ſufficient proffe of thys mattier. <hi>Quum</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut. xxiii.</note> 
                  <hi>uotum uoueris domino deo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uo, non tardabis reddere, quia require<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> illud dominus deustuus, &amp; ſi mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus fueris, reputabitur tib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:26296:73"/> catum. Si nolueris polliceri, absq peccato eris. Quod autem egreſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt de labijs tuis, obſeruabis, &amp; faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mathe this ye vo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ries and repente the breache of your vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes in time</note> 
                  <hi>ſicut promiſiſti domino deo tuo, &amp; propria voluntate, &amp; ore tuo locutus es.</hi> When thou haſte vowed a vowe vnto thy Lorde God thou ſhalt not be ſlacke to paye it, becauſe thy lorde God wyll require it of thee, and if thou ſhalt be ſlowe or ſlacke, to perfourme thy vowe, thou ſhalt ſinne. If thou wilt not make a vowe, thou ſhalte be withoute ſynne, concerninge this pointe. But thou ſhalte kepe, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d doe that thing, whiche is ones gone out of thy lyppes, as tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> haſte promiſed to thy lorde God, and haſte ſpoken with thyne owne free wyll, and mouthe. Oh how manifeſte is thys texte againſte
<pb facs="tcp:26296:73"/> the breakers of their vowes of chaſtitee, voluntarie pouerte, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, and all other that are <note place="margin">Reade this.</note> good &amp; godlie, as theſe thre are? Why remembre they not that Chriſt would not ſuffre a man, which he had called to be a prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chour of his worde, to burie his <note place="margin">Matth. viii <hi>Theoph.</hi> Luc. ix.</note> owne father, declarynge therby that euerye man ſhoulde ſerue God in hys owne vocation, and not leaue it, or do any thinge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pungnaunt to the ſame Doeth not Chriſt exhort vs to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre <note place="margin">Luc. xvii. Gen. xix.</note> Lothes wyfe, that we looke not backewarde from our vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and callinge? Sayed not Chriſt alſo to one that ſayed, I wyll <note place="margin">Luc ix.</note> followe the o Lorde, but let me firſt take my leaue of them that are at home in my houſe? No man putteth hys hande to the
<pb facs="tcp:26296:74"/> plowe, and loketh backe, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hynde him, is apt to the realme, or kingdome of God? And doth not thei loke behinde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which forſake their profeſſion, &amp; kinde of lyfe wyllingly choſen to ſerue God in? Saint Paule commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth, yea Chriſte ſpeakinge in <note place="margin">i. Cor. vii. ii. Cor. xiii.</note> him, that euery man ſhoulde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde in hys owne vocation. Dothe they ſo, that breake their vowes of chaſtitee, &amp; pouertie? Did not ſaint Peter by the puiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaunce, and power geuen to him of God, ſtryke Ananias, and Saphyra to death for breaking <note place="margin">Act. v. <hi>Fulgentius epi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtola i. Cyprianus lib. i. ca. xxv. aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Iudaos.</hi>
                  </note> their promiſſe, and vowe made to the holye ghooſt, whiche was in reſeruiuge to themſelfes a piece of the money gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ſale of their fielde, where they hadde promiſed to geue the whole vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:26296:74"/> thapoſtles, for their ſuſtina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; the pooers, as then had done manye good men, willynglye <note place="margin">Act. iiii.</note> without any commaundement of God, followinge therin onely Chriſtes counſell? Saint Baſyl <note place="margin">Matth. xix. <hi>Lib. de inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tione ad vitam perfectam.</hi>
                  </note> proueth by thys place, that men ought to kepe all their vowes of virginitie, contine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, chaſtite, pouerte, of abſtine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, of faſting, and ſemblable others.</p>
               <p>Sainte Bede, whiche was <note place="margin">Lib. i. ca. xxiii. hiſt. anglorum</note> our countreeman, and liued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue. DCCC. threſcorre yeres paſſed, witneſſeth that ſainte Gregorie the firſt Pope of that <note place="margin">Anno. do. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> name, ſente one ſainte Auſten w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> almoſt fourtie other learned good men into thys our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tree Englande to conuerte it vnto the fayth of Chriſt agayne, and that when the kinge Edilber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thus,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:75"/> and manye others hadde receaued the faieth of Chriſte, the ſaied Auſten was made by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Cantorburie, and that then he wrote to the Pope Gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gorie, to be inſtructed of hym, howe the Byſhoppes and the cleargie ſhoulde lyue amongeſt the people, or howe manye por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhoulde be made of the thynges, whiche thorowe the <note place="margin">Lib. 8. ca. xxvii hiſtaeccleſe An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glorium.</note> faithful peoples oblatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s came to the aulter, and howe the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ſhoulde vſe himſelfe in the churche. Vnto whiche demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the Pope ſainte Gregorie made thys aunſwere. The ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the apoſtles ſeate <note place="margin">Howe by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſhuld deſpende their goodes</note> at Rome is to teach byſhoppes created, or made, that of euerye ſtipende, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth to them, foure partes or portions ought
<pb facs="tcp:26296:75"/> to be made, one for the byſhop, and hys familie, and to receaue ſtraungers, and to kepe hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>litie with. The ſeconde for the nourriture &amp; ſuſtentation of the cleargie. The thirde part ſhould be geuen to the poore people. The fourthe ought to be reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and diſpended vpon the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payringe of hys churches: But for as muche as, ſaieth he, thye brotherhoode hathe ben inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted in the rules of ſolitarie ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge, <note place="margin">Religious men, albeit they were byſhoppes oughte to haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per.</note> and of religion, you maye not lyue ſeuerallye from youre clerkes, ye muſt ordeyne thys conuerſation, &amp; thus leade your lyfe in England, as the fathers did euen at the beginnynge of Chriſtes churche, amongeſt the whiche euerye thynge that they <note place="margin">Act. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. iiii.</note> had, was commen, and they had
<pb facs="tcp:26296:76"/> nothinge propre. Thys leaſſon gaue that holye father ſainte Gregorie the Pope vnto that byſhop, whiche was afore a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious perſone, and to hys com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>panions, that were Monkes. Whiche counſell beinge groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <note place="margin">Note this.</note> vpon the ſcriptures, &amp; their vowe, all religious men &amp; wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men oughte to followe vppon payne of damnation. But I <note place="margin">The olde. doctours vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon vowes.</note> wyl recite ſome of the olde god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye fathers ſayinges, written of them againſt prieſtes preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed mariages that they may ſee euidentlye, howe they erre in the defenſe of theym, and that they ſtande in daunger of euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſtynge damnation continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge in that opinion.</p>
               <p>S. Fulgentius writteth theſe <note place="margin">Fulgentius epi. prima de debi to coniugali.</note> wordes. Saintes Paule pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth
<pb facs="tcp:26296:76"/> that wydowes are in daunger of damnation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they haue a mynde to <note place="margin">i. Tim v.</note> marrye after they haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed chaſtitye. <hi>Quàm ſit autem malum, quàm<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſollicite effugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum, ſi quis de hoc, quod domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no vouerit, aut retinere, aut repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere aliquid, mortificatione, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentet, exemplo ſunt Ananias &amp;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. v.</note> 
                  <hi>Saphyra, quos de precio agri quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam partem infoeliciter ſubtrahen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, non ſolum vox apoſtolica, tan<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> diuini iuris peruaſores in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre puit, ſed etiam ſeueritas iuſtitiae coeleſtis occidit. Si quis igitur rem iam deuotam, carnali victus illece<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bra, crediderit denuo repoſcenda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, non eſt legitimus rei poſſeſſor, ſed diuini iuris pronunciatur inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor. Nec immerito continenciae
<pb facs="tcp:26296:77"/> iam deuotae violator immu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dus au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, quod pecuniae auarus audiuit. haec ille.</hi> Is not thys manifeſtly written agaynſte breakers of <note place="margin">Marke this ye votaries and vowe breakers.</note> theyr vowes of chaſtity, &amp; volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarye pouertie? Se we not here moſt manifeſtly what great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god, yea what great da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation in hel the votaries doe incurre, which voluntarily haue broken their vowes, &amp; now doe obſtinatly ſtyll perſeuer in their fleſhly &amp; fylthy wickednes, moſt blyndly, moſt boldly, &amp; moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperatly drowned in carnal luſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out recouerie or hope of ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement? Do not all men ſe here alſo how they haue falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſine to ſinne, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer one ſinne hath ben puniſſhed by an other more greuous: And this is one of the greateſt puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may be,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:77"/> But of thys matter I wyll by Goddes helpe, ſpeake more at large in another treatiſe.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Some of the auncient doctours ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, written agaynſt the marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of them, whiche had made a vowe of continuall chaſtitie, and continencie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cumenius</hi> an olde Greake writer thus hathe, declaringe <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> i. Cor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> theſe Sayncte Paules wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des: If a Vyrgen doe marrie ſhe ſynneth not. <hi>Varginem hoc loco appellat, non eam, quae Deo conſecrata eſt, ſed innuptam puel lam. Nam quae Deo conſecrata eſt.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>ſi nupſerit, Chriſto reddit cum adulterum, cui nubit.</hi> When S. Paule ſayth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> yf a virgin mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye, ſhe offendeth not God, he calleth not her in thys place a
<pb facs="tcp:26296:78"/> virgin, whiche is whollye ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to God by a vowe of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitie, but a damſell or a wenche vnmaried. For yf ſhe marrie, <note place="margin">Reade ye married no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of dan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger.</note> whiche hathe vowed chaſtitie, or virginitie, ſhe maketh him, to whome ſhe marrieth, an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutrer agaynſte Chriſte her huſbande. The godly and good Chriſtian Emperour, Iouini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <note place="margin">Tripar. hiſto. lib. 7. cap. 4.</note> made a lawe, that who ſo euer married a nonne, or a vir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gin, that had vowed chaſtitie, ſhoulde ſuffer death therfore.</p>
                  <p>S. Hierom is playnlye agaynſt <note place="margin">Hierom. lib. i. contra Iouinia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> the marriages of theym, that haue vowed chaſtitie, writyng after this ſorte vpon theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of Paule. If a virgin doe marrie, ſhe doeth not ſynne. <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Lim. v.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Non illa virgo, quae ſemet cultui Dei dedicauit. Harum enim ſi
<pb facs="tcp:26296:78"/> quae nupſerit, habebit damnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, quia primam fidem irri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam fecit.</hi> Paule ſayinge, yf a virgin marrye, ſhe ſynneth not, dyd not meane that virgin, whiche had once for euer geuen her ſelfe by a vowe of chaſtitie, or virginitie, to ſerue, or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe God. For yf anye one of them ſhall marrye, ſhe ſhall be damned, becauſe ſhe hathe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken her fyrſte faythe, geuen to God, when ſhe vowed to hym virginitie. Peter Martyr fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowynge therein the frere De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colampadius, Bucer, and other the Lutherians, and Swing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians, whiche marryed agaynſt their profeſſions and vowes, affirmeth and defendeth with a ſhameles face, that it is not lawefull to vowe continuall
<pb facs="tcp:26296:79"/> chaſtitie, and that men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men may without faulte mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, althoughe they had vowed the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Is this to refourme Chriſtes religion defaced (as they at the leaſt doe pretende) and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> it agayne to her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> eſtate and pureneſſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> was at the beginninge of the churche? But heare S. Hierem agayne ſayinge: <hi>Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes quae poſt conſecrationem nup</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> i. contra Iouimanum.</note> 
                     <hi>ſerint, non tam adulterae ſunt, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ceſiae.</hi> The virgins whiche doe marrie after their profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are not ſo muche aduoutreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as ſynners agaynſt theyr promiſſe made to their ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all eſpouſe Chriſt. Reade hym <hi>ad Sabinianum,</hi> where he ſayeth, that he which marrieth a no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, committeth aduoutrie agaynſt
<pb facs="tcp:26296:79"/> Chriſt her ſpouſe, and huſband. Heare nowe Epiphanius, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che was almoſte xii. hundreth <note place="margin">Epiphanius co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra apoſtolicor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> haereſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. anno do mini. 369.</note> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> paſſed, and ſayeth. <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlde unt ſancti Dei apoſtoli, pec <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> eſſe poſt decretam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ad nuptias conuerti: Et ſcrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> apoſtolus. Si nupſerit vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go non peccauit. Quo modo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> hoc cum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> concordar? Imo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> virginem dicit, quae non eſt dicata Deo. &amp; ce.</hi> The ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Apoſtles of GOD haue <note place="margin">The ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles lawe that vowes ſhoulde be kepte.</note> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aughte, that it is ſynne, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> vnto marriage after vir ginifie is decreed to be kepte.</p>
                  <p>And the Apoſtle Paule hathe written. If a virgin do marrye ſhe hath not ſynned. How th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> doeth this ſaying of S. Paule agree with that the Apoſtles teachynge? Yea the Apoſtle ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:26296:80"/> ſpeaketh of that virgin, whiche is not offered, or geuen to the ſeruice of God by a vow of chaſtitie. Ambroſe accordeth with thys godlye doctrine whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſayth. <hi>Melius eſt nubere, quàm</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Ambroſius ad virgine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. cap. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. i. de iuſtificatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne virginis. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. et lib. 3. virginitate.</note> 
                     <hi>uri Hoc apoſtolicum dictum non ad pollicitam pertinet, ad non du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> velatam. Coeferum, quae ſe ſpopondit Chriſto, &amp; ſanctum velamen accepit, iam nupſit, iam immortall iuncta eſt viro. Et iam ſi voluerit nubere communi lege connubij, adulterium perpetrat, ancilla mortis efficitur.</hi> It is better to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye then to burne. Thys ſaying of the apoſtle appertaineth not to her, which is promiſed to god by a vowe, to her that is not yet couered with a vele. But ſhee, whiche hathe promiſed herſelfe to Chriſte to be hys eſpouſe, or
<pb facs="tcp:26296:80"/> wyfe, and hathe taken the holie vayle, is nowe maried, is nowe ioyned vnto an imortal huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. And if ſhe wil now marie by the commen lawe of mariage, ſhee committeth aduoutrie, ſhe is made the bonde ſeruaunte of death. Is it not then a great madnes to followe Peter Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryr, <note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ca. vii. de pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorum &amp;c. Lib. de hareſ. ca. lxxxii.</note> doctour Thomas Cran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer, and ſuch others defending the hereſie of Iouinian, condem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned by ſaint Auſten, ſaint Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roin and manye other notable clerkes, and to forſake theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye fathers leſſons, the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of diuers counſelles, <note place="margin">Con. Elibertinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca. xiii. ſub Sil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueſtri. Con. Chalce. cap. xvi.</note> eſtabliſhed with the worde of God? Our lorde God of his ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre goodnes, and great mercye take this blyndnes out of mens hartes, that they may retourne
<pb facs="tcp:26296:81"/> vnto the catholyke churche, out of the which they are gone, and are cleane diuided from it by a ſciſme mooſte dainuable, when they forſoke the mother churche (as ſainte Ireneus and ſainte Cyprian calleth it) whiche is Rome. The greate learned man ſainte Baſill wrote muche <note place="margin">Baſillius lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> virginitate.</note> againſt this hereſie, for he ſaith. <hi>Virginitatem domino profeſſae, deinde à carnis voluptatibus conci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ratae, ſcortationis peccatum, nupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arum nomine uolunt uelare. &amp; ce.</hi> They haue profeſſed virginitie to our Lorde, and afterwarde <note place="margin">Reade ye Nunnes, that haue maried.</note> beinge ſterred by the luſtes or pleaſures of the fleſhe, woulde couer their horedome with the name of mariage. What can Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter Martyr the chanon, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:26296:81"/> votaries, that haue maried women, ſaye to theſe auncient doctours ſayinges Would they that men ſhoulde rather beleue their ignoraunte iudgementes, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe fathers excellent lear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned ſentences? Dothe they not plainlye de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clare themſelfes to be ſchiſmarikes, and no me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres of the catholyke churche, when they diſſent from theſe, and the other holye wryters beleife and teachinge? Agayne ſau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Baſill ſpekynge of religious perſones, <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap> &amp; xv.</note> whiche had de vowed chaſtitee ſuch as are Monkes, Nunnes, and Chano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſayeth. <hi>Horum v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſquis<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſi poſtea<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> inter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> rum fratrum focietatem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> fuerit, factam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> reſciderit, is perinde aſpici debet, ut qui in deum peccauerr, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb facs="tcp:26296:82"/> uidelicet profeſſionis teſtem adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buerit, cui<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſe uoto ſolemni obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garit. Etenim qui ſeipſum deo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel deuouit, hicſi ad aliud deinde uitae genus tranſierit, ſacrilegij ſe ſcelere obſtrinxit, quip pe qui ſeip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum deo, cuiſe conſecrauerat, ue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luti ſuperfuratus ſit.</hi> If anye one of theſe, after he is ones choſen into the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paignie of the other brethren, ſhall breake hys pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, <note place="margin">Reade this ye votaries and repence the breaking of your vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes.</note> he muſt or ought ſo to be loked vpon, as he, whiche offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded God, whom he toke a wir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of hys profeſſion, and to whom he bounde himſelfe with a ſolemne vowe. For he, whiche hathe made to God a ſolem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e promeſſe, or vowe, if he goe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde to an other kinde of lyfe, hath bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>den himſeire with the haynous ſynne of ſacrileage
<pb facs="tcp:26296:82"/> becauſe he as it were, ſtealeth himſelfe from God, vnto whom <note place="margin">Lege Baſilium epi. lxiii. libro conſtitutionum monaſticarum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. &amp; ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> nachu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lapſum.</note> he had wholy geuen himſelf. Is not thys plainly ſpoken againſt the chanon Peter Martyr, and ſeinblable others, that haue bro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken their vowes of chaſtitee, and voiuntarie pouerte? In an other place ſainte Baſill layeth <note place="margin">Epiſt. ad virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem lapſam.</note> a greate reproche to a virgyn, that hadde brooken the ſolemne vowe of her profeſſion made w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the veſture, or habite of a profeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed Nunne. I let paſſe manye other ſentences of thys holy doc tour. To be breife ſaint Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is agaynſt this hereſie, which wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thus. <hi>Quod cui<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ante<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> uo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſſer,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Auguſt. lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. cap xxiiii. ad p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>llentium.</note> 
                     <hi>licebat, quum id ſe nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quam facturum vouerit, non lice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>it. Si id uouerit, quod uouendum fuit, ſicut eſt perpetua virginitas vel co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <pb facs="tcp:26296:83"/> tinentia, poſt experta connubia ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutis á uinculo coniugali, uel ex conſenſu uonentibus &amp;c.</hi> He that <note place="margin">The vowe of vouertie. ought to be kept.</note> hathe, ſayeth he, made a vowe of perpetuall virginitee, or of continence euer to endure al his lyfe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> els of pouerte, he maye in no caſe breeke that hys vow, becauſe our Lorde hathe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded that vowes ſhoulde be kept, ſayinge thus. <hi>Vouete, &amp;</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Scal. lxxiii.</note> 
                     <hi>reddite domino deo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ueſtro.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Make ye a vowe, and render it to your lord God. Alſo he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth by thys ſentence of Dauid nowe alleaged here, that it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte Gods commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to breeke a vowe of chaſtitee, &amp; other vowes, when he ſayth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap> Armentar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> riparium &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> nam epi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> thys manier. <hi>Non re vouiſle paeniteat, imo gaudeiam tibi ſic no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> licere, quod cum detrimento tuo licuiſſet.</hi> Do thou not repent,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:83"/> that thou haſte vowed, naye ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reioyce, and bee glade that that thyng is not now leeful for the to do, whiche thou myghteſt haue doone leefullye with thye dommage. To be breife, and to let paſſe manye of his ſayinges in thys matter, he ſayeth. <hi>Quid ait apoſtolus de quibuſdam quae</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">To. viii. in pſal, lxxv. <hi>i. Limo. v.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>uouerunt &amp; non reddiderunt? Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentes inquit, damnationem, quia primam fidem irritam fecerunt. Quid eſt primam fidem irritam fecerunt? Vouerunt, &amp; non reddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derunt.</hi> What ſayeth the apoſtle <note place="margin">Lege cum in pſal. lxxxiii. de bono viduitatis ca. ix. x. xi.</note> S. Paule of certen wydowe, whiche haue vowed chaſtitee, &amp; haue not kepte their vowes? They haue, ſayeth Paule, dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, becauſe they haue broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their fyrſte fayeth, what thinge <note place="margin">Note this reader dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>entlye.</note> is that, they haue broken their firſte faieth? They haue
<pb facs="tcp:26296:84"/> vowed, and kepte not their pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſe, or vowe. Who wyil then geue anye further credence to our newe goſpellers in any one pointe of their damnable opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſeinge they do herin erre ſo manifeſtly both againſt the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſcriptures, and the auncient doctours expoundinge the ſame to vs? Alſo he affirmeth that no <note place="margin">Lib de bono viductatis ca. 8</note> woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which, hath vowed cha ſtitee maye leefullye afterward marrye, but ſhe runneth therby into euerlaſtyng damnation: &amp; groundeth hys ſaying vpon the texte of ſaint Paule laſte aboue reherſed. But heare nowe ſaint <note place="margin">1. <hi>Limo. v.</hi> Chryſoſt, homi. de fide, ſpe, &amp; charitate.</note> Chryſoſtome in thys mattier ſayinge thus <hi>Si aliud geſseris, ꝙ voueris, &amp; fidei nomen perfida uo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntate diſsolueris, non modo prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miorum compos eſse non poteris
<pb facs="tcp:26296:84"/> ſed &amp; deſtinato ſupplicio, neceſse eſt, ſubiugeris.</hi> If thou ſhalte doe <note place="margin">Reade this ye votaru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> anye thynge againſt thy vowe, &amp; ſhalt breeke the name of faith. or faithfulnes, with an vnfaith full wyll, thou ſhalt not onelye loſe thy rewarde, but thou muſte nedes be puniſhed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynglye as God hathe deter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mined. Againe he writeth thus expoundynge theſe S. Paules wordes. If a vyrgin do marrye <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. 4. homi. xix. in. i. Co. vii</note> ſhe ſynneth not. <hi>Ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> de ea, quae ſibi virginitatem elegerit, loqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quippe quae iam peccauit. Nam ſi viduae, quae ſecundis ſe nuptijs alligarunt, iudicium ſubeunt, ſiſe mel uiduitatem elegerint. multo magis virgines.</hi> Sainte Paule ſayinge, if a virgyn do marrye, <note place="margin">i. Lim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> ſhe ſynneth not, ſpeaketh not of her, that hathe ones choſen to
<pb facs="tcp:26296:85"/> herſelfe virginitee, becauſe ſhee hathe nowe ſynned. For if wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, whiche hathe bounde themſelfes to the ſeconde mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, are vnder the perell of dampnation, if they ones haue choſen by a vowe to continue widowes, and after that do ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye, muche more virgyns. What can be moore playneiye ſpoken agaynſt the votaries, Nunnes, Monkes, Chanons, &amp; Freers, that haue maried againſt their vowes made to God? Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome ſayeth alſo that the mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages of Monkes are worſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <note place="margin">Tom. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. 21. ad Theodorum monachu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vbi ait monachum contrahentem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere adulio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> eo peiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> cri deſignare.</note> aduoutrye. Seeſt thou not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, good reader, euidently that Pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter Martyr, doctour Thomas Cra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer late archebiſhoppe of Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>torburye, Ridlye, Latymer, Iohn Hoper, Rogers, doctour
<pb facs="tcp:26296:85"/> Crome, and all the reſt of that ſorte are nor of the catholyke churche, out of the whiche there <note place="margin">i. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> iii.</note> is no ſaluation, but ſchiſmaty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, and deuided clearelye from the companie of them that ſhalbe ſaued, ſeynge they beleue not as theſe holye fathers dyd, which are nowe ſaintes in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen? Is then anye man ſo fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe to beleue their doctrine, touchyng the bleſſed ſacrament of the aulter, the holye Maſſe, and ſuche other mattiers of our faieth, lately called into queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and doubte, by them, after they had forſaken the vnitee of the catholyke church? But heare ſaint Cypria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which was almoſt <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> m. c c c. yeres ſence &amp; a holy Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyr. <hi>Quu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſtus virgine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuà <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> dedicata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctitati ſuae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb facs="tcp:26296:86"/> iacere cum altero cernit, quàm in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignatur, et iraſcitur, et quas pae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas inceſtis eiuſmodi coniunctio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minatur?</hi> When Chryſte ſeeth hys virgin, geuen to hym by a vowe of virginitee, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to his holynes, lye with an other, howe muche is he mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued &amp; angrie? And what peynes threteneth he to ſuch an vuleful mariage, whiche is worſe then aduoutrie? Agayne he ſayeth. <note place="margin">Cypria. de du plici martyrio. Lege eu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de habi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis virginum.</note> 
                     <hi>Nonne uide mus totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eccleſiae coe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum vultus dimittere, at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> erubeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, quoties aliqua virgo, quae chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſto nupſerat, dilapſa ex angelico contubernio, defecit ad ſtuprum, aut coniugium?</hi> Do we not ſee al the whole compaigine of the churche loke downe with theyr countenaunces, and to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as often as anye virgyn,
<pb facs="tcp:26296:86"/> whiche had maryed to Chriſte by a vowe of virginitie, fallen downe from the companye of aungels, forſoke her profeſſion by committiuge of horedome, or by marryage?</p>
                  <p>The ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ye Pope Leo fyrſte of that name, whiche was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue. xi. hundred yeares paſſed commended wonderfully of the generall counſel holden at Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedo beynge therein aſſembled D C. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. learned fathers, ſaith this of Monkes. <hi>Propoſitum</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Leo primus Epiſt. 9 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>monachi proprio arbitrio, aut vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntate ſulceptum, deſeri non poteſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> peccato.</hi> The pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of a monke taken with his owne arbitriment or wyll, can <note place="margin">That had vow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ertie.</note> not be lefte vndoue withoute ſyane. But let this be ſayde in thys controuerſie, as ſufficient
<pb facs="tcp:26296:87"/> to eſtabliſhe the trouth thereof, and to ouerthrowe the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Nowe heare a lytle moore of the vowe of pouertie, and of the kepynge of it, albeit, that which is already ſpoken therof, myght be ſufficient, for the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunt to learne the trueth of this matter, and to ſee in what daunger they be, whyche doe breake that vowe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>That the vowe of pouertie ought to be obſerued of monkes; nonnes, chanons, frere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and all other reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious perſons vpon the payne of damnation.</head>
                  <p>For aſmuche as, good reader, many good men thynke that it is lawefull for a man that hathe made a vowe of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie pouertie, to enioye
<pb facs="tcp:26296:87"/> rycheſſes in propre, or to haue the proprietie of goodes, I thoughte it verie neceſſarie to traicte briefely of that matter, that men myghte the better knowe the trueth therein, for the dilchargynge of their owne conſciences towardes God.</p>
                  <p>The authorities ufore written, out of the ſcriptures touchinge vowes, doe proue ſufficientlye that y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed willingly pouertie, to haue nothig proper, he or ſhe is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to kepe this ſame vowe vnder payn of euerlaſtyng damnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and the ſame doeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the church teach, amon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geſt the which theſe are ſome of their ſayinges that here folow. S. Auſcen intreatinge of mon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 line">
                           <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> ſayeth. <hi>Nemo quicquam
<pb facs="tcp:26296:88"/> poſsidet propriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nemo cuiquam oneroſus eſt.</hi> None of them poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth any thyng as hys owne proper goodes, no man is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to an other. Alſo he ſayeth <note place="margin">Aug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ciuitace dei</note> that the Apoſtles (the lyfe of whome monkes ſhoulde folow in that poynte) profeſſed and vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wed pouertie, which S. Peter declared, when he ſayde to <note place="margin">Math. xix.</note> Chriſt. Beholde, we haue lefte all thynges. <hi>Alius vult relinque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Ang<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n pſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>omnia ſua, diſtribuendo ea pau peribus, et ire in communem vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, in ſocietatem ſanctorum, magnum votu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vouit. Vnuſquis<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> reddat deo, quod vouit.</hi> An other man doth vow to forſake al his goodes, diſtributinge and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidynge them to the poore, and to go into a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon lyfe, wherin all thynges are common, and
<pb facs="tcp:26296:88"/> nothynge propre, and to go into the felowſhip of the holye, he hathe made a greate vowe to God. Let euery man paye, or re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre to God, that thynge, whiche he hathe vowed to him. Sainte Chryſoſtome was of that ſame <note place="margin">Tractatis ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus vitupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratores monaſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cae vitae.</note> mynde, ſayinge. In Monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries all thynges are commen, meum, &amp; tuum, myne, and thine, whiche de trouble all the whole worlde are taken awaye there. Item he ſayeth: <hi>In monaſterijs no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. homi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>viis ad pop. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ochenum.</note> 
                     <hi>eſt meum, &amp; tuum, ſed hoc uerbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eliminatum eſt, infinitorum cauſa bellorum.</hi> In monaſteries is not myne and thyne, but this word, whiche is the cauſe of infinite battaylles, is putte out of thoſe houſes.</p>
                  <p>The holye Pope Vrbane, an <note place="margin">Vrbanus papa lib. de bonis ec cleſiarum &amp; re ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munione.</note> auncient great clearke wryteth
<pb facs="tcp:26296:89"/> after thys ſorte. <hi>Quicun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> veſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> communem ſuſcepit uitam, et nihil ſe habere vouit, videat ne pollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationem ſuam irritam faciat, ſed hoc, quod domino eſt pollicitus, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deliter cuſtodiat; ne damnationem, ſed praemium ſibi acquirat &amp;c.</hi> Whiche ſo euer of you, ſayeth he, hathe taken vpon hym a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <note place="margin">Note ye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficed vota<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries.</note> lyfe, &amp; hathe made a vowe to haue nothinge propre, let him ſee, or take hede and beware, that he breake not his promiſſe, but kepe faithfullye that thing, whiche he hath promiſed to our Lorde, that he gette not to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe damnation, but a rewarde of God. Our lorde geue that grace to all votaries, whiche haue made a vowe of pouertie, to beware of breakinge of it, leaſt they for lucre and gaines
<pb facs="tcp:26296:89"/> of a litle worldlye goodes, looſe the eternall, and heauenlye ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Amen.</p>
                  <p>But heare ſaint Hierom ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge. <hi>Non eſt ubi eadem cauſa, quae</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">To. i. epiſ. i ad helioderum.</note> 
                     <hi>coeteris. Dominum auſculta dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem. Si uis perfectus eſſe, vade, &amp; vende omnia, &amp; da pauperibus, &amp; ſequere me. Tu autem perfec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum re fore pollicitus es. Nam cum derelicta militia, te caſt raſti propter regna coelorum, quid aliud ꝙ per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectam ſecutus es vitam. Perfectus autem ſeruus Chriſti, nihil praeter chriſtum habet. Aut ſi quid praeter chriſtum habet, perfectus non eſt. Et ſi perfectus non eſt, cum ſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum fore deo pollicitus ſit, ante mentitus eſt. Os autem, quod me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur, occidit animam, Igitur ut con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cludam,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Sapienc. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>ſi perfectus es, cur bona paterna deſideras? Dominum fefel
<pb facs="tcp:26296:90"/> liſti, ſi perfectus non es. Alia eſt monachorum cauſa, alia clericoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Clerici paſcunt oues, ego paſcor.</hi> Agayn he ſaieth vnto a monke. <note place="margin">To. i. ad vuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> 
                     <hi>Tu vero, ſi monachus eſse vis, non uideri, habeto curam, non rei fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaris, cui renunciando, hoc eſſe cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſti, ſed animae tuae.</hi> But if thou wilt be a monke in dede, and not to appeare onlye, care not for the goodes belonginge to thy familie, or houſehold, which thou haſte forſaken, to be a Monke, but take care of thye ſoule. He ſayeth alſo. <hi>Vidi ego quoſdam, qui poſtquam renuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eade ye monkes and chanous.</note> 
                        <hi>ſaeculo, ueſtimentis dumta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>at et uocis profeſſione, non rebus, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil de priſtina conuerſatione mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarunt. Res familiaris magis aucta, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m imminuta. Eade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miniſteria ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ulorum, idem apparatus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiuij.
<pb facs="tcp:26296:90"/> Idem ad paulinum de inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tione</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> mona<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>iait. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>officium uis exercere preſbyteri, ſi epiſcopat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> te vel opus, vel honor force deiectat, viue vrbibus, vel caſtellis, &amp; alioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſalutem, fac lucrum animae tuae. Sim aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> capis eſſe, quo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>iceris, monachus, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>eſt, ſolus, quid facis in vrbibus, quae uti<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> non ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum habitacala, ſed multorum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>am non ſunt tua; quae poſſides, ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> penſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tio tibicredita eſt. Memento</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Act. v.</note> 
                     <hi>Ananiae at Sapphyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, Illi ſua timi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ſerr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>erunt, tu conſidera, ne chriſti <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> imprudenter effundas, id eſt, ne immoderato iudicio rem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> trib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>as, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pauperibus.</hi> Is not this manifeſt lye ſayd againſt religious men, that haue benefices, prebendes, and other promotions, where they haue vowed pouertie, and
<pb facs="tcp:26296:91"/> made a promes in the tyme of their profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to haue nothinge as their owne, and propre to themſelfes, but to lyue in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mone God geue to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grace, and to all others, to ſerue him deuoutly, that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bye they maye pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſſe vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfs the glorie of heauen, thorowe Gods mercye, and the deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of oure Lorde Ieſu Chriſte</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:26296:91"/>
            <p>Imprinted at London by Robert Caly, within the precinct of the late diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued houſe of the graye Freers, nowe conuerted to an hoſpital, called Chriſtes hoſpitall.</p>
            <p>M. D. LV.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
